<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Heir followeth the coppie of the ressoning which was betuix the abbote of Crosraguell and John Knox, in Mayboill concern ing [sic] the masse, in the yeare of God, a thousand fiue hundreth thre scoir and two yeares.</title>
            <author>Knox, John,</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1563</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00239</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S93406</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633312</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633312</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174733</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00239)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174733)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2121:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Heir followeth the coppie of the ressoning which was betuix the abbote of Crosraguell and John Knox, in Mayboill concern ing [sic] the masse, in the yeare of God, a thousand fiue hundreth thre scoir and two yeares.</title>
                  <author>Knox, John,</author>
                  <author>Kennedy, Quintin, 1520-1564.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 32 [i.e. 64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Robert Lekpreuik, and are to be solde at his hous, at the nether bow. Cum priuilegio.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Jmprinted at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1563.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: [fingerpost]⁴, [maltese cross]⁴, [fingerpost]⁴, A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Numbered pages on recto only.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print bleeding and show-through, with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mass --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174733:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174733:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Heir followeth the coppie of the reſſoning which was betuix the Abbote of Croſraguell and Iohn Knox, in Mayboill concerning the maſſe, in the yeare of God, a thouſand fiue hundreth thre ſcoir and two yeares.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Apocalips. xxij.</bibl>
For I proteſt vnto euerie man that heareth the wordes of the prophecie of this boke: If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall adde vnto theſe thinges, God ſhall adde vnto him the plagues, that are written in this boke.</q>
            <p>Imprinted at Edinburgh by Robert Lekpreuik, and are to be ſolde at his hous, at the nether bow.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio.</p>
            <p>1563.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:174733:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174733:2"/>
            <head>Iohn Knox vnto the reader, wiſheth grace mercie and peace, from God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and from our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte: with the ſpirit of righteous iudgement. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the Prophet Iſayas in great ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemencie, had rebuked the vanitie of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolles, and Idolaters as in the 40.<note place="margin">Iſa. 40 and 41.</note> and 41. chapters, of his prophecie doeth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, at laſt he burſteth forth in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Let them bring forth there Gods (ſaeth he) that they may ſhaw vnto vs thinges that are to come, or let them declare vnto vs thinges that haue bene done before. &amp;c. Shaw thinges that are to come, that we may vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you to be Gods, let you do ether good or euill, that we may declare it. By which wordes, the Prophet doeth as it were in mockage, prouoke Idolaters, and the Idoles to produce for them ſelues, ſome euident teſtimonies by the which me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might be aſſured, that in them was power, and that there religion had approbation of God. which when they could not do, he is bold to prononce this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: Behold ye are of nothing,<note place="margin">Iſa. 41.</note> and your making is of nothing, abomination hath choſen you. In which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the Prophet damneth, bothe the Idoles, &amp; the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters. The Idoles, becauſe they can declare nothing to proue any power or wertue to be in them, why they ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uld be worſhipped as Gods. And the Idolaters, becauſe from Gods month they could bring no aſſurance of there addulterat and vſurped religion. If this reaſoning of the Prophet, had ſufficient ſtrength in his aige, to ſhaw the vanitie of the Idoles, and the phrenetick fooliſhnes of ſuche as worſhipped them: then may the godlie this day moſte aſſuredly conclude againſt the great Idole pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the Papiſtes to be worſhipped in there maſſe, and againſt the patrons of the ſame: that it and they are
<pb facs="tcp:174733:3"/>
vaine, fooliſh, odious, and abominable before God. It, becauſe it hath mo makers then euer had the Idoles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt the Gentiles: and yet hath no greater power, then they had. Albeit it hath bene worſhipped as God him ſelf. And they becauſe, they worſhipped there owne imagination, and the workmanſhip of there own ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, without any aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God or of his word. If any think that I ſpeak more liberally, then I am able to proue, let him conſider what makers the Idoles of the Gentiles had, and what makers the God of bread hath. And then let the power of bothe be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared, and let me be rebuked, if I ſpeak not the treuth. The Prophet in diſcription of there vanities, maketh theſe gries. The earth bringeth forth the tree, it groweth by moiſtour, and natural wack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, it is cutted doun by the hand of the hew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t. A parte thereof is burnt, a parte ſpent in vſes neceſſarie to man, an other parte choſen to be made an Idole. This is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the licknes of man or woman, and then ſet vp and worſhipped as a God. All theſe and ſome mo, ſhall we find to aſſiſt &amp; concurre in the making of this great God of bread. The wheat is ſowen and nouriſhed in the earth, rain, dew, and heat bring it to maturitie. The reaper or ſcherer cutteth it doune, the carte or fled, drawen by hors or ſome other beaſt, draweth it to the barne, or to the barnȝaird. The taſker, or the foot of the ox tradeth it out. The fan deliuereth it from the chaff. The millar, and the milſtones by the help of wind or watter, maketh it to be meall. The ſmith maketh the yrnes, that giues to that God, his lenth and breaid, licknes and form. The fyne ſubſtance of that God is nether wood, gold, nor ſiluer, but watter &amp; meal made i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maner of a dra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mock. And then muſt the workmen take good hede to there hand. For if the fyre be to hote, that Gods ſkin muſt be burnt, if the yrnes be euill dight, his face wilbe blecked, if in making the roundnes, the ring be broken, then muſt an oher of his fellowes, receaue that honor to be made a God, and the craſed or cracked miſerable caik, that ones was i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hope to be made a God, muſt be giuen to a babby to play him withall. And yet is not all the danger paſt, for if there be not an anoynted preiſt to play his parte aright, all the formar artificers haue loſt there laboure, for without him that God can not be made: yea, if he haue not inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate, the faſhioned God remaueth bread, and
<pb facs="tcp:174733:3"/>
ſo the blind people committ Idolatrie.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the artificers and workmen that trauell in making of this God: I think as many in nomber, as the Prophet reciteth to haue trauelled in making of the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. And if the power of bothe ſhalbe compared, I think they ſhalbe found in all thinges equall, except that the God of bread is ſubiect vnto mo dangers then were the Idoles of the Gentilles. Men made them. Men make it. They were deaf and dum, it can not ſpeak, hear nor ſee. Brieflie in infirmitie, they wholie aggre, except that (as I haue ſaid) the poore God of bread is moſte miſerable of all other Idoles. For according to there matter whereof they are made, they will remaine without corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares. But within one year, that God will putrifie, &amp; then he muſt be burnt. They can abyde the vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the wind, froſt, rain, or ſnow. But the wind will blow that God to the ſea, the rain or the ſnow wil make it dagh again, yea, which is moſt of all to be feared, that God is a pray (if he be not wel kept) to rattes and miſe. For they will deſyre no better denner then white rounde Gods ynew. But o then what becometh of Chriſtes na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural bodie? by myrackle, it flies to the heauen againe, if the papiſts teach treulie, for how ſone ſoeuer the mouſe takes hold, ſo ſone flieth Chriſt away &amp; letteth hir gnow the bread. A bold and puiſſant mouſe, but a feble and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable God? Yet wold I aſk a queſtion, whether hath the preiſt or the mouſe greater power? by his wordes it is made a God, by hir teith it ceaſeth to be a God. Let them auiſe, and then anſwer. If any think that I oght not to mock, that which the world ſo long hath hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and great Princes yet holde in ſo great venerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I anſwer, that not onelie I, but alſo all godlie oght not onelie to mock, but alſo to curſe and deteſt, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is not God, and yet vſurpeth the name, power, and honor of God. And alſo that we oght bothe to mock, gain ſay, and abhorr, all religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obtruded to the people, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out aſſurance of God &amp; his word, hauing nether reſpect, to antiquitie, to multitude, to authoritie, nor eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of them that mantean the ſame. The Idoles of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles were more ancient, then is the Idole in the maſſe. There worſhippers, manteners, and patrons, were mo in multitude, greater in authoritie, and more excellent before the world, then euer was any that bowed to that
<pb facs="tcp:174733:4"/>
Idole.<note place="margin">Iſa. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> And yet feared not the Prophet Iſayas to mock and ieſt them, yea, ſharplie to rebuke them, in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. They are dung backward with ſhame, they ſhalbe aſhamed, whoſoeuer truſteth in a grauen ymage, and that ſay to the molten ymage,<note place="margin">Iſa. 44.</note> ye are our Gods. All the makers of graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ymages are vaine, there pleaſing thing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es ſhall not proffet them. For they themſelues are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, to there Idoles, that they nether ſe, nor vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any thing, and therefore they ſhalbe aſhamed, who then (ſayeth he) ſhall forge a God? or a molten ymage that profiteth nothing? behold all thoſe that are of the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thereof ſhalbe confounded, for the workmen them ſelues are men, let them all be gathered together, and ſtand vp, yet they ſhall feare and be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded together. And when he hath fully painted forth there vanitie, he concludeth. They haue not vnderſtand, for God hath ſhut vp there eyes,<note place="margin">Blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and indura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is Gods iuſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters.</note> that they can not ſee, and hartes, that they can not vnderſtand, none conſidereth in his hart, I haue brunt half of it, euen in the fyre, and haue baken bread alſo vpon the coalles thereof I haue roſted fleſhe &amp; earen it, and ſhall I make the reſidew thereof an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſhall I bow to the ſtock of a tree? &amp;c. Thus, I ſay, we ſee, how that the Prophet doeth triumph againſt the Idolaters, in mocking of there madnes, and painti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g forth of there vanitie. Who then can iuſtlie be offended againſt me or any other albeit by all meanes poſſible, we let the blind world ſee, the vanitie of that Idole? conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that by it, hath the glorie of God bene more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured, then euer it was by any Idole in the earth. For to none was neuer abſolutlie giuen,<note place="margin">Let the Papiſts conſider</note> the name, nature, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and honor of God, but to that Idole allone. If any think that the Scriptures of God giue vnto them patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinie, ether to beleue Chriſtes naturall body to be there, after the wordes of conſecration (as they cal them) ether yet to beleue that Chriſt Ieſus, in his laſt Supper, did offer vnto God his Father his body and blood, vnder the formes of bread and wine, he is miſerablie deceaued, for the Scripture maketh no mention, of conuerſion or tranſubſtanciation of bread in Chriſtes naturall bodie, but witneſſeth that bread remaneth bread, yea eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when the faithfull receaue the ſame,<note place="margin">1. Cor 10</note> as the Apoſtle affirmeth in theſe wordes. The bread that we break, is it not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of Chriſtes bodie? the cup of bliſſing which
<pb facs="tcp:174733:4"/>
we bliſſe, is it not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the blood of Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> we many, are one bread, and one body, becauſe we are all partakers of one bread. And after he ſayeth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> as of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as ye ſhall eat of this bread, and drink of this cup, ye ſhew the Lordes death till he come. Let therefore, a man try him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and ſo let him eat of this bread, and drink of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. By theſe wordes we may clearlie vnderſtand, what iudgement the Apoſtle had of the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, euen in the verie action of the ſame. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that fooliſh opinion, that Chriſt Ieſus did offer his body vnto God his Father, vnder the formes of bread &amp; wine. &amp;c. (which the Papiſtes make the ground of there maſſe) what ſuffrage that euer it hath by man, of God, nor of his word, it hath none.<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.</note> The Scripture dooth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that God the Father gaue his Sone vnto the world, that the world might be ſaued by him, and that Ieſus Chriſt did offer him ſelf ones vnto God,<note place="margin">Heb. 10 and 9.</note> for the deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinne, and for to take away the ſinnes of many, but that euer he did offer him ſelf vnder the formes of bread and wine (as the Papiſtes alledge) the holy Goſte doeth no where make mention. And therefore the faithfull not onely may reiect it as the dreame and inuention of man, but alſo are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to abhor &amp; deteſt it as a doctrine broght in by Satan, to deceaue ſuche as delyte not in the veritie of God, to whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and voice are the faithfull onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. M. Quintyne that great patron of the maſſe, in this ſubſequent conference,<note place="margin">Maiſter Quinty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes affir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>matiue.</note> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ieds for the probation of his affirmatiue, Chriſt Ieſus did offer (ſayeth he) vnto God his Father, in his laſt Supper his body and blood, vnder the formes of bread and wine. &amp;c. For the probation hereof, I ſay he adduces the fact of Melchiſedec that broght forth bread and wine.<note place="margin">Gen. 14.</note> &amp;c. But how ſone he is aſhamed thereof and how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able he is to proue that which he alledgeth to be moſte e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſie to be prouen, the diligent reader may eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y. For per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing him ſelf unable euer to proue,<note place="margin">Luk the reſſonig of the thrid day.</note> that ether Chriſte Ieſus or yet Melchiſedec, did make any ſuche oblation, as he &amp; the fond Papiſtes do imagine. He ri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth ſtraight to his fortres &amp; ſhameles ſchift. O ſayeth M. Quintyne, I haue hurt my own cauſe, I was caried away with zeal &amp;c. It apperteaned not vnto me to proue any thing, but to defend my artickles as they are written. If M. O.
<pb facs="tcp:174733:5"/>
and his collat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ralles will reſolue me an dout, then will I giue my iudgement, whether he oght to proue, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend onely. My dout is this, whether are M. Quintynes artickles neceſſarie to be beleued to Saluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or are they ſuche as without danger of damnation, we may dout of them? If we may dout of them and not offend God, then aſſuredly I think that M. Quintyne may hold them for treuth, til that the falſhead of them be manifeſtly declared. But if they be ſuche as we are bound to beleue as a treuth of God, and an doctrine neceſſarie to Saluation, then is M. Quintyne bound to ſhaw to vs that God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonced them, and not man. which if he be not able to do, and that in plaine and expreſſed wordes, then muſt we reiect them as deceauable,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> &amp; fals, accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as we be taucht by our maiſter Chriſt Ieſus ſaying: My ſheip heare my voice, but a ſtranger they will not heare. If M. Q. will not be reputed an fals Prophet, &amp; one that teacheth lies in the name of God, and ſo expone him ſelf to Gods here diſpleaſure, he may propone no doctrine to the Church of God, the aſſurance whereof, he bringeth not from the mouth of God. If M. Q. were brawling in the ſcooles, or bragging of knowledge amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the Philoſophers, I wold pacientlie abyde, that he ſhould affirme as many paradoxes, as pleaſeth him. But in the Church of God to affirme that God hath ſpoken, when God hath not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or done that which he is not able to proue, by his plaine word, that he hath done, ſo to do (I ſay) is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether intollerable, and therefore let M. Q. ſearche the Scriptures, for the probation of his affirmatiue, or els I will cry als loud as I can, that he hath loſt his cauſe, and is conuicted an manifeſt lear: in that he hath affirmed Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus to haue done that, which no Scripture doeth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that he hath done. Let all men therefore that will not follow lies, deteſt the maſſe, till that it find a ground within the booke of God, as I am aſſured it neuer ſhall. And that ſhall the reader more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylie perceaue, by this confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that followeth.</p>
            <p>Read and then iudge.</p>
            <p>☞ <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ☜</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:174733:5"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The abbotes firſt letter.</head>
                  <byline>M. Quintyne.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohn Knox I am informed, that &amp;c ar cum in this cuntrie, to fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and in ſpecial to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pugnation to certane artickles quh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> war pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and reheirſed be me to my ſtock, in Kirkoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wald on ſonday laſt wes (treulie I will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe diſputation with ȝow) bot maiſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nſtlie &amp; effectuouſlie couatis the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it may be to ye glorie of God, and tryall of ye treath, lyke as I haif, ye reſt of ye miniſters, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uhilk h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s bene heir, and culd haifna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e. Quhair <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore gif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t pleis ȝow this day viij dayes in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay hous of Mayboi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ȝe pleis, prouidand alwayes thair be na com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation paſſand xii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vj or xx on ather ſyde, quhil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is ane ſufficient nomber: to beir witnes be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uir vs, I ſal enter in reſtoring with ȝow, and God willing fall defend ye ſaides artickles be ye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt word of God, and all gude reſſon, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> writtin, and in ſpecial ye artickle concern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ye meſſe. Ȝe ſalbe ſure ȝe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> reſſaif na im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> of me, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> that me p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>nis, nor na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of moleſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or work, bot familiar, formall, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ll reſtoring; and think not y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> this is done for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ng of tyme; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be reſſone I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>eit and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be my Lord of Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>is, in name and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the counſel, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> or any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning
<pb facs="tcp:174733:6"/>
in the cuntrie, quhais command I haif promiſt to obey, nottheles and he cum not betuix and the ſaid day, I ſall diſcharge my promis to him with diligence, quhairthrouch ȝe, and all v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may ſe how deſyrous I am that ye treuth cum to ane tryall but drifting of tyme. Als ȝe may be ſure that I am verray deſyrous to haif my Lord of Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llis (as my cheif and brother ſone) and vthers my brether &amp; freindes, quhom of I haif charge, to be auditors, quhairthrow gif it pleis God thay micht haif proffet of our reſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and gif ȝe pleis to accept this condicion, ſend me ȝour promes vnder ȝour hand writ, and I ſall ſend ȝow the foreſaid artickles to awiſe on, to this day viii dayes, and in the meine time ȝe may prouide to be auditors ſic as ȝe pleis, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to the nomber aboue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>heirſed, and I the lyke, and gif ȝe will nawiſe enter in reſſoning without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uocation of ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, the haill warld may ſe, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rbario<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tumultuation, and cummer that ȝe ſeik, vnder the pretence of the trew ſetting furth of Goddes word, and glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and this I certifie ȝow, I will not enter in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation with ȝow, gif ȝe eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uocation, for I wil nawiſe be the inſtrument of diſcorde,<note place="margin">The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thereof was ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. But my lord ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>id no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply.</note> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> als it is not neceſſar &amp;c <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m with conuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſtrangers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ȝe ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my Lord of Camilis pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to ȝow, and all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tick, and in ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne ȝe pleis to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>giſme qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and to ȝow with the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and gif ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:174733:6"/>
the ſamin weill, ȝe ar mair able to mak impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to myne. Of thir heides I require ȝour anſwer in writ, with this herat with diligence quhaitthrow I may ſend away to my Lord of Caſſillis as ſaid is. And ſa fair ȝe weill, of Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raguell this Sonday, the ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of September.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Crofraguell</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head> the anſwer to the abbotes firſt lettter.</head>
                  <byline>Iohn Knox.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He treuth is, that the cauſe of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in theſe partes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſeak diſputation, but ſimplie to propone vnto the people Ieſus Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cuſſed, to be the onelie Sauiour of the world, and to teach further, what are the fruites that God requireth of the members of his dear ſone. &amp;c. But heauing that ye had in oppen audience proclamed blaſphemous artickles, making pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to giue further declaratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of certane of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this laſt Sonday, lykewiſe in oppen aſſemblie, I could not but of conſcience, offer my ſelf to be your aduerſat in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ace. And this far for the cauſe of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming ȝeſterday to k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>hoſ wai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:174733:7"/>That ye haue required diſputation of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters (of whome ſome are yet preſent) &amp; could haue none, I hardlie beleue it, the contrary be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured to me by diuers of honeſt report.</p>
                  <p>That ye offer vnto me familiar, formall, and gentill reaſoning with my whole hart I accept the condition. For aſſuredlie my Lord (ſo I ſtyle you by reaſon of blood and not of office) chiding &amp; brawling I vtterlie abhor, but that ye require it to be ſecrete, I nether ſe iuſt cauſe why that ye ſhould require it, nether yet good reſon why that I ſhould grant it. Yf ye feare tumult asye pretex, that is more to be feared where many of euill mynd haue a few quiet and peceable men in there danger, then where a iuſt multitud may gainſt and violence, if it be offered. Of my Lord of Caſſilles promes, I nothing dout as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my owne perſon, for I ſtand in the protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Almightie, to whom I render hartly thankes, when his mercie and power boweth the hartes of men, to aſſiſt the cauſe of the iuſt.</p>
                  <p>But I wonder with what conſcience ye can require priuat conference of thoſe artickles that ye haue publicklie proponed? Ye haue infected the eares of the ſimple? Ye haue wounded the hartes of the godlie, and ye haue ſpoken blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie in oppen audience. Let your owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence now be iudge, if we be bound to anſwer you in the audience of 20. or 40. of whom the one half are alreadie perſuaded in the treuth, &amp; the other perchance ſo addicted to your error, that they will not be content, that light be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:174733:7"/>
light, and darcknes, darcknes. Yf ye be a paſtor as ye brag your ſelf to be, ye oght to haue reſpect to your whole flock, yea, to the inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all thoſe, that are offended at your blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies. But now to grant vnto you, more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaſon, I am content of the greateſt nomber ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by you, prouided firſt that the place be. S. Iohnes kirk in Air, which is a place more conuenient then any hous in Mayboill. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darlie, that Noters and Scribes be appointed faithfully to take and commit to regeſter, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen audience, bothe your reaſones, and myne, that ſo we may aſwea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> auoid confuſion &amp; vaine repeticion in ſpeaking as forclos the diuerſitie of rumors, which may ariſe by reaſon of obliuion, what hath bene ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ather partie. The day by you required. I can not kepe, by reaſon of my formar promes made to the maiſter of Maxwel, and vnto the Churches of Niddiſdall, and Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loway. But if ye wil ſend vnto me, your artick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les before the 15. of this inſtant, I ſhal appoint the day, which by the grace of God I ſhal not faill. Yf ye ſend your artickles to the baillies of Air, it ſhalbe ſufficient diſcharge for you. And thus crauing your anſwer, I hartlie deſire God if his good pleaſure be, ſo to molifie your hart, that ye may prefer his eternal treuth, conteined and expreſſed in his holy word, to your own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceaued opinion. From Air this 7. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember. 1562. in haiſt.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Youres to command in all godlines. Iohn Knox</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174733:8"/>
                  <head>the abbotes ſecond letter, whereunto anſwer is made brieflie to euerie head of the ſame.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohn Knox I reſſaned your writing, this monu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day the ſeuint of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and conſidered the heides thairof, and firſt quhair ȝe ſay, ȝour cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in this cuntrie, was not to ſeik diſputation, but ſimplie to propone vnto the people, Ieſus Chriſt crucified, to be the onely Sauiour of the warld, praiſe be to God, that was na newingis in this cuntrie, or ȝe war borne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>I greatlie dout, if euer Chriſt Ieſus wes treu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie preached, by a papiſticall prelat or monk.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Secondlie, quhair ȝe alledge that I proclamed in oppen audience blaſphemous artickles (he is ane euill iudge that condemnis or he knowes) than had bene tyme to ȝow to haif called them blaſphemous, quhen ȝe had ſene them, red them, and ſufficientlie confutated them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>I had hard them, and thereof I feared not to pronunce them ſuche as they are.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Thridly, quhair ȝe alledge that I promiſt decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſaides artickles, on Sunday laſt
<pb facs="tcp:174733:8"/>
was, my promes was (as my hand writ will teſtifie) to do the ſamin, ꝓuidand alwayes yair had bene na conuocation of ſtrangers, quhair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw tumultuation and cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer micht follow, and ſwa was I exonered of my promes, in that, ȝe come thair conuoied with v. or vj. ſcoir of ſtrangers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>I lay the night before in Mayboil, accompanied with fewer then tuentie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Apperantlie mair lyke to ſeik perturbation and cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer, nor the glorie of God. Als I was inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit be my Lord of Caſſillis to his returne in the cuntrie, as I wrait to ȝow of before, for auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mers. Ferdlie, gif I required diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Iohn Villock, and als of maiſter george Hay, gif thay had ocht to ſay to ony warkes ſet furth be me, I report me to the auditor, and als gif thay refuſed or not, to the tyme thay had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed with the counſell and the brethren.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>Maiſter george Hay offered vnto you diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but ye fled the barras.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Quhair to ſay ȝe can not per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>hairfore. I ſould deſyre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ere it deſputation. Treulie it is not ſecreit, that is in the preſence of al perſones. Quhair ȝe ſay ȝe do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> not of my Lord of Caſſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis promes, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> perſon. Treu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie apperanlie ȝe refer als lytil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>omes as ȝe may, conſidering ȝe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome conuoyed with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ie one nomber of ſtrangers as is aboue reheirſed.
<pb facs="tcp:174733:9"/>
Quhair ȝe ſay, ȝe ſtand in the protection of the Almichtie, ſwa dois all gude chriſtiane men as ȝe, bot apperanlie ȝe put als lytil in Gods hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is as ȝe may, that gois accompanied in euerie place, quhairſumeuer ȝe go with ſic multitude, quhidder it be for deuotion, or protection, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tumultuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God knawis, for I knaw not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>Ye do well to ſuſpend iudgement.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Quhair ȝe wonder with quhat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience I can require priuat conference (treulie I haif mony gude reſſonis mouand me) firſt to auoid tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, perturbation, and cummer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>Your reaſones are as ſtark to your ſelfe, as ye think them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Secondly, that we may haif ane reſſonable no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that may beir witnes of baith our pairtes, but clamor or tumultuation. Thridly, I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane gif we cum to the iuſt tryall of the treuth, chair man be conference of mony buikes, quhilk can not be done co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modiouſly in publick audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Attoure it wilbe mair handſum and eaſie for me, nor miſteris not ſic crying out, as gif it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> in oppe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audience, for gif ye victorie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt in clamde, or cryi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g out, I wil quite yow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe but father pley, and ȝit praiſe be to God, I may quhiſper in ſic maner as I wilbe hard ſufficientlie in the largeſt hous in all catrick.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:174733:9"/>The larger hous, the better for the auditor &amp; me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Quhair ȝe ſay I haif infected the earis of the ſimple I haif wounded the hartes of the godlie, and I haif ſpoken blaſphemie in oppen audie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. I meruell how ȝe forȝet ȝour ſelf, chidand and railland on this maner.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſpeaking of the treuth is chiding vnto you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Conſidering ȝe ſaid ane lytill afore, ȝe did abhor all chiding and railling, bot nature paſſis nurtor with ȝaw.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>I will nether interchange, nature nor nurtor with yow, for all the proffets of Croſraguell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Quhairfore I man beir with ȝour babline and barking, as dous Preices, hear poweris Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtrates, and mony hundrethes better nor I. Quhair ȝe eſteme me as ane bragand Paſtor, ſay and, that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>cht to haif reſpect to my haill flock. It is queſtion to me gif it de the weill of my flock, to mak oppen diſputation in profound myſteries concerning the chriſtiane religion, but ȝit will I not refuſe gif ony man will mak im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnation, but conuocation of ſtrangers, or tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuation, I haif hard of publick diſputation in ſcoulis, but not afore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne vulgar and rude mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>titude of people.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>Ye are not then ſo weall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ne in the ancient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as ye brag.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                     <p>Quhair ȝe deſyre me to cum to diſpute in S.
<pb facs="tcp:174733:10"/>
Iohnes Kirk of Air, ȝe may be ſure I will not diſpute with ȝow thair,<note place="margin">My lord delytes in ryme without reaſon.</note> for mony gude reſſonis, quhilkis to write, war ouer prolitt, bot gif ȝe pleis to conueine according to my firſt writing, I ſalbe readie at all tymes, vpon viii. dayes warning, and ſall ſend yow the artickles viij. dayes afore to auiſe with. And ſa fait ye weill. Of Croſraguell with diligence, the famin day and daie. CROSRAGUELL.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                     <p>THis letter wes none otherwiſe anſwered for that tyme, but by appointing vnto him the place, according to his owne deſyre, albeit that no reaſon could haue required that of me.</p>
                  </sp>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Earle of Caſſilis letter.</head>
                  <p>EFter hartlie commendation, forſameklil as I vnderſtand thair is ane diſputation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed betuix yow, &amp; the abbote of Croſraguell in Mayboill, the xxviij. of this inſtant, to the quhilk I am not willing that ony of myne mak diſputation with ȝow, except it cum of ȝour oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, for I can not vnderſtand that ony erudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fall proceid to the auditor of the famin, bot rather contradiction and tumult, the quhilk. I wald ſould not be for ȝour pairt, lyke as I am willing to cauſe the abbote of Croſraguel to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. As to quhaſaeuer that wil proffer them ſelf to preach the trew word, conform to the conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
<pb facs="tcp:174733:10"/>
of the realme, may do the famin without impediment as I wrait to ȝow of before, in ony of my rowmes. And deſires ȝow to write me ane anſwer of this writing, and God keip ȝow. Of Sainct Iohnes chapell the xxiij. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember. 1562.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Be ȝour gude freind. Caſſillis</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>the anſwer to my Lorde of Caſſillis writing.</head>
                  <byline>Iohn Knox.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter hartlie commendation, of my ſeruice vnto your lordſhip, your L. letter dated at S. Iohnes chapell the xxiii. of this inſtant, receaued I in Vghiltrie the xxv. of the ſame. As touching the diſputation appointed, the occaſion did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cead of the abbote, who in oppen audience of the people, did propone certaine artickles, whereof the moſte part conteane deceauable doctrine, whiche nottheles he promiſed not onely to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, but alſo to manteane againſt any that wold impugne the ſame. Whereof I being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed, and ſo near in the countrie could do no les then offer my ſelf aduerſary to that doctrine, which I am aſſured ſhalbe certaine damnation, to all thoſe that without repentance depart this
<pb facs="tcp:174733:11"/>
life, infected with the ſame. And vpon that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue I repared to Kirkoſwald, where becauſe the abbote compered not, I preached, and after the Sermon a ſeruand of the abbotes preſented vnto me a letter, conteaning in effect, that as he had required diſputation of the other miniſters, ſo did he of me, and did appoint vnto me, that day eight dayes in Mayboill. My anſwer wes, that to diſpute I wes hartlie content, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I had before appointed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maiſter of Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel to be in Dumfreis that ſame day, I deſired the day to be prolonged, to my returning from Netheſdaill. In this meane tyme by letters paſt betuix vs the xxviij. of this inſtant is appointed which day be the grace of God I mynd to keap. Nether yet in my iudgement is there any iuſt feare of tumult, for the perſones that ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uene with me, will promes and keap all quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and of your lordſhip I nothing dout but ye will take ſuche ordour with your freindes, that by them there ſhall no occaſion of trouble be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and albeit that the erudicion ſhal not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance be ſuche as the godlie wold deſyre, yet I dout not bothe the veritie and the falſhead ſhall appeare in there owne colors, albeit not to all, yet to ſuche as ether haue eares to hear y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treuth plainly ſpoken, or eyes to diſcerne darcknes from light.<note place="margin">Let the abbote iudge if he had iuſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to accuſe me as he after do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> And therefore I wold moſte humblie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of your lordſhip, rather to prouoke and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curage your freind to the ſaid diſputation, then in any maner to ſtay him, for if your lordſhip do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider that whil, that he oppenlie preaches one
<pb facs="tcp:174733:11"/>
thing, and we an other, that the hartes of the people are diſtract, yea, and inflambed one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, your lordſhip ſhould rather feare tumult and trouble to enſew thereof, then of mutuall conference, in the audience of peceable and quiet men. The nomber is not great that is admitted to hear, and therefore trouble is les to be feared. Pleaſe your lordſhip to vnderſtand that the veritie oght to be to vs, more deare then our owne liues, and therefore we may not leaue the mantenance of the ſame, for feare of that whereof the iſhew is in the handes of God, to whoſe protection I moſte hartlie commit your lordſhip. Of Vghiltrie in haiſt the ſame houre your lordſhips letter wes receaued. 1562.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours lordſhip is to command in all godlines. Iohn Knox</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>the abbotes thrid letter anſwered by mouth.</head>
                  <byline>M. Quintyne.</byline>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ohn Knox I perſaif the policie vſed be ȝow and vthers, to mak my awin ay my partie. The laſt tyme ȝe come in this cuntrie,<note place="margin">Brag o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t</note> I was perſuaded be my Lord of Caſſillis not to rancounter ȝow, or
<pb facs="tcp:174733:12"/>
els treulie ȝe ſuld not haif paſſed vnrancou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tered as ȝe did, bot ȝe ſalbe aſſured I ſal keip day and place in Mayboill according to my writing, and I haif my life, and my feit louſe, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ony writing that is cumin to me, fra my Lord of Caſſillis, therefore keip tryſt, and excuſe ȝow not vpon my Lorde of Caſſillis writing, notwithſtanding that I knaw it is purcheſt be ȝour policie,<note place="margin">Ye kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we that, as ye knowe that mel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chiſedec offerred bread &amp; wine vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to God, whiche two ye are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer able to proue</note> to put me to ſchame, and ȝour ſelf to aduanſment, quhilk ſall not ly in ȝour power, thairfore I aſſure ȝow, in cace I ſould do the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min with the haiſſart of my lyfe, do ȝe the lyke without excuſe. And ſa fair ȝe weill. Of Croſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guell this xxiiij. of September. 1562. Attoure that thair be na conuocation bot conforme to ȝour writing, or els thre ſcoir at the maiſt, of the quhilkis tuentie to be auditors on ather ſyde.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CROSRAGUELL.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The abbotes fourt letter.</head>
                  <byline>M. Quintyne.</byline>
                  <p>IOhn Knox and baiillies of Air, this preſent is till aduertiſe ȝow that I reſſaued writing and credit with this gentle man, fra my Lord of Caſſillis, certifi and me that he will keip day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for our diſputation, thairfore keip ȝour promes, and pretex na ioukrie be my Lorde of Caſſillis writing. And this fair ȝe weill. Of Croſraguell the xxv. of September. 1562.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CROSRAGUELL.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb facs="tcp:174733:12"/>
                  <head>The anſwer to the abbotes fourt let.</head>
                  <byline>Iohn Knox.</byline>
                  <p>TO nether of theſe did I anſwer otherwiſe, then by appointing the day, and promiſing to keap the ſame. For I can pacientlie ſuffer wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone men to ſpeak wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie, conſidering that I had ſufficientlie anſwered my Lord of Caſſillis in that behalf.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>SOme other letters are omitted becauſe they were of les importance, follow the condict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>THe day houre, condicions and nomber ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greid vpon, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ference betuix maiſter Quintyne Kennedy abbote of Croſraguell, and Iohn Knox miniſter at Edinburgh.</head>
                  <p>The day is the xxviij of September. 1562. The place the Proueſtis place of Mayboill, the houre to conuene is at eight houres before none, the day foreſaid, the nomber for euerie part ſhall be fourtie perſones, by there Scribes &amp; learned men, with ſo many mo as the hous may goodly hold, be the ſight of my Lord of Caſſillis.</p>
                  <p>And heirupon, bothe the ſaid abbote and Iohn Knox are wholylie and fullylie agreed. In wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes whereof they haue ſubſcriued theſe preſents with there handes. At Mayboill the xxvij. of September. 1562.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>Croſraguell</item>
                           <item>Iohn Knox</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:174733:13"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He nomber receaued within the hous foreſaid, and ſo many beſydes as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my Lord and his freindes. Iohn Knox addreſſed him to make publict prayer, whereat the abbote wes ſoir offended at the firſt, but whil the ſaid Iohn wold in no wiſe be ſtayed, he and his gaue audience, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, the abbote ſaid be my faith it is weil ſaid. And ſo after that he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken certane wordes, he comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded one of his Scribes to read openly his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>☞ <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ☜</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:174733:13"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="dialogue">
                        <head>Heir followes the coppie of the reſſoning quhilk wes betuix the commendator of Croſraguell and Iohn Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap> in Mayboile concerning the maſſe, in the yeare of God. 1562.</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erceauing the great perturbation con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouerſie and debeate, quhilk is ſtirred vp laitlie in all Chriſten realmes, for the cauſe of religion (honorable auditor) and als be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remembred of the terrible ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence conteined in ſcriptures toward all negligent paſtors in this dangerous tyme. I was conſtrayned in conſcience notwithſtanding my great inhabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as it pleaſed God to ſupport my imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones to giue inſtruction to all thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to my cure, within my Kirk of Kirkoſwald, how they ſhoulde be able to be enarmed againſt all wicked and decetfull preachers quhilk gaes about not knowing quher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>fra they come, nor by quha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> ordre. And to the effect that our deirlie-beloued flock micht haue bene the more able to haue bene warre with all fals wicked &amp; vngodly doctrine. Amang other godlie leſſones contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in my exhortation I inſerit certane catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick artickles hauing their warrand of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures of almighty God, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of the halie catholicke Kirk, and burdyned my
<pb facs="tcp:174733:14"/>
conſcience in the preſence of God the ſaides ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickles to be godlie, neceſſarie and expedient to be beleued by all good chriſtiane men.</p>
                           <p>Iohn Knox vpon ſonday the aucht day of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, came vnto the ſaid Kirk of Kirkoſwald, being certefied that I might not be preſent, and as I was enformed to make impugnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to my ſaides artickles wherethrough I wrote to him, certifying that I wold affirm the ſaides artick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and in ſpeciall the artickle concerning the maſſe againſt him or quhaſoeuer pleaſes to make impugnation there to vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aucht dayes warning, the place being in any hous of Mayboyle, the nomber tuentie on either ſyde, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conuocation.</p>
                           <p>Shortlie we being agreed by writing of the day hour and place, quhilk was the 28. day of this inſtant September. I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men conforme to my writing to affirme the ſaides artickles as they are written, beginning at the artickle concerning the maſſe. Proteſting alwayes that I come not to diſpute any of my artickles as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith &amp; religion diſputable, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering there is ordre taken alreadie by the Kirk of God (as I wold ſay) be the generall councelles, deulie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uened quhilk repreſents the vniuerſal Kirk of almighty God to whom it apperteines to take ordre quhenſoeuer queſtion riſes for maters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning faith and religion, but according to the doctrine of S. Peter and als S. Paule to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my dett and duetie to all that inquires ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and after that maner to abyde gentle and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174733:14"/>
formall reaſoning of all that pleaſes, as may ſtand to the glorie of God and the inſtruction of the auditor. And to the effect foreſaid that we may come to formal reſſoning, as to ward the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the maſſe, I wil ground me v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Scriptures of almightie God, to be my warrand co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forme to my firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation, quhlik was gathered vpon the prieſthead and oblation of Melchiſedec: and was preſentet ȝou in Februare, and as ȝit has gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no anſwer, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that it was of ſober quantitie ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene or 20 lynes. Wherfore pleaſe you to receaue this ſame confirmation yet as of before for to be the beginning of our formall reaſoning, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the artickle of the maſſe in maner as after followes. The Pſalmeſt &amp; als the Apoſtle S. Paule affirmes our Saluiour to be an prieſt for euer, according to the ordure of Melchiſedec, quha made oblation and Sacrifice of bread and wine vnto God as the Scripture plainly teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es vs: now will I reaſon on this maner.</p>
                           <p>Read all the Euangell wha pleaſes, he ſall find in no place of the Euangel quhere our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour vſes the prieſthead of Melchiſedec, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring him ſelf to be an prieſt after the ordor of Melchiſedec, but in the latter Supper, quhere he made oblation of his precious body &amp; blude vnder the forme of bread and wine prefigurate by the oblation of Melchiſedec: then are we compelled to affirme that our Sauiour made oblation of his bodie &amp; blude in the latter Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or els he was not an prieſt according to the
<pb facs="tcp:174733:15"/>
ordor of Melchiſedec, quhilk is expres againſt the Scripture.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Iohne Knox proteſted that he mght haue the coppie of this formar writting giuen in by my Lord in writ, to anſwer therto more fullie, &amp; at greater leaſer, which was deliuered vnto him.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Quintene.</speaker>
                           <p>And in lykemaner, my Lorde proteſted that he might haue place to reply, if he thoght good.</p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="writ">
                        <head>The anſwer of Iohn Knox to the Abbottes oration, giuen in by the Abbote before the diſputation, in writ.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Knox.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Henſoeuer it pleaſeth God of his great mercy, to ſhew the light and to blow the trompet of his true word vnto the blind &amp; vnthankful world, after darknes and lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſilence, it hath the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to moue and walken not onelie the choſen, but alſo the reprobate, but in diuerſe maner: for the one it walkeneth, from ignorance, error, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticion, vanitie, and horrible corruption, to walk before there God in knowledge, veritie, true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of his maieſtie, and in puritie of life. But the other it walkeneth from there formar <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>iueth, and yet to there further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation. For ſuche as in the time of darknes did liue as men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſound of the trompet, calling them to repentance, addes and ioynes to there format corruption, blaſphemie againſt God, and againſt his eternal veritie. For perceauing that the light
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174733:15"/>
diſcouereth there turpitud, and that the trompet wil not ſuffer them to ſlepe, as that they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without open reproche:<note place="margin">Iſay. 5.</note> they ſhame not to call light, darknes: &amp; darknes, light: good, euil: and euil, good. And to bring that to pas, to wit, that the light ſhine no more, doeth the whole ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of ſuche as oppone them ſelues to the veritie of God, ſo earneſtlie trauell, that ſtugardes and effeminat men become actiue and ſtrong Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioures to the Deuil. The exemples hereof are in Scriptures ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon that they nead no long rehearſal. For what was the eſtate of the fals Prophetes and Preaſtes in the dayes of Iſayas, Ieremie, Ezechiel, Micheas and the reſt of the true Prophetes of God.</p>
                        <p>What care (I ſay) they which by ordinarie ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oght to haue teached the people of God, tooke ouer there charges, the complaintes &amp; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of the true Prophetes vſed againſt them do witnes.<note place="margin">Iſay. 56. Read the place.</note> In the which they call them dum dogs, blind watchemen, ſuche as regarded nothing but ambition, tyarous cheare and luſtes of the fleſh.<note place="margin">Ezeh. 34</note>
                        </p>
                        <p>Paſtors that fedd not the flock, but fedd them ſelues. Finally they terme them,<note place="margin">Iere. 6.</note> men from the moſte to the leaſt, giuen to auarcie, apoſtattes that had left God, his lawes, ſtatutes, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and had laid them ſelues doun to ſleape in the middes of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the which they could not be walkened.</p>
                        <p>But yet how vigilant and actiue they were to reſiſt the true Prophetes and the doctrine offred
<pb facs="tcp:174733:16"/>
by them, the Scripture doeth lykwiſe teſtifie. For then wes Iſayas and ſuche as adheared to his doctrine,<note place="margin">Iſay. 8</note> holden as monſters in the eyes of the proude preaſtes,<note place="margin">Iere. 38</note> and of the multitude. Then was Ieremie accuſed of treaſon, caſt in preſone, and dampned to death.<note place="margin">1. Re. 22</note> Then wes Micheas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly ſtriken vpon the mouth, and briefly then did none of the true Prophetes of God eſcape the hatred and cruel perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe that cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the title and authorie to rule in the Church. The ſame may be ſene in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of Ieſus Chriſt: for how negligent and careles wes the whole leuiticall ordor (a few excepted) theſe wordes of our maiſter Ieſus Chriſte do witnes.<note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> wo be vnto you Scribes and Phariſes Hipocrites, for ye ſteak the kingdome of heauen before men: ye your ſelues do not enter, and ſuche as wold en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ye ſuffer not. But when the trompet began to blowe in the mouth of Iohn the Baptiſt, and when Ieſus Chriſte began to preache &amp; to make mo diſciples then Iohn did, when Iohn called them progenie of vipers and Ieſus Chriſte did terme them blinde guides, how careful was the whole rable then?<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> Is eaſie to be eſpyed. For then were ambaſſadours ſend to Iohn to knowe by what authoritie he made ſuche innouation amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge the people and in the religion of God.<note place="margin">Mat. 15.</note> Then was Chriſte Ieſus tempted with ſharpe &amp; ſubtil queſtions.<note place="margin">Mat. 17.</note> Then was he accuſed for breaking of the tradicſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es of the ancients. Then was he cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Beelzebub, And in the end he was procured to be hanged betuex two theues. And by whoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174733:16"/>
diligence wes all this broght to pas? wes it not by them who before had abuſed the law? blinded the people, deceaued the ſimple, and vnder the title and name of God had ſett vp the deuil and all abomination to ring ouer men?</p>
                        <p>For in place of Gods true worſhipping they had erected a market,<note place="margin">Ioh. 2.</note> and filthie merchandriſe in the temple of God.</p>
                        <p>The eiection whereof did ſo enrage thoſe dum dogs that with an bay they began to barke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.</note> and his moſte holſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine: and that becauſe the zeale of that great God, their bellie, did altogether conſume and eat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp. Theſe thinges we knowe to be moſte true, and therefore we oght not to wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der albeit the true worde of God reteane the own nature, and that the ſelf ſame thing chance now in our dayes that heretofore hath bene fully performed. As for my ſelf I nothing dou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> but the great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbation, controuerſie, and debate, laſtly ſtirred vp in all chriſten realmes, for cauſe of religion, is the cauſe that my Lorde abbote hath be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e of lait dayes troubled to vnaccuſtomed la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>boures. For if the ſuperſticion, idolatrie, pride, vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ambition, vniuſt poſſeſſions,<note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe why Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſts ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ow ſo di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligent in preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</note> ſuperfluous rentes and filthy liuing vſed &amp; manteyned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore by ſuche as clame the name and authoritie of the Church had not bene openly rebuked and a parte therof in diſpyte of Sathan ſupreſſed it may be thoght that my Lorde in this his impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent age could haue contented him ſelf with the ſelf ſame eaſe and quietnes that in his yonger
<pb facs="tcp:174733:17"/>
age and better habilitie, he enioyed. But now the tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet ſoundeth dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all negligent paſtors, and thereof is my Lorde afrayed, and therefore to diſcharge his conſcience he wil take the paine to inſtruct his flock, &amp; to warne them to be ware of fals teachers. I wil interprete all to the beſt part, if my Lordes eye be ſingle, his worke is good. But if the light that appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to be in him,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> and in his ſect, be nothing but darcknes, how great ſhall the darcknes be? my Lorde is a clerk &amp; nedeth no interpreter of ſuche places of Scripture. Yet for the ſimple (I ſay) that rightlie to teach the flock of Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">Trew know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is required in a trew preacher</note> requireth right inſtitucion in Chriſtes own doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. For els a zeale without knowledge is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the cauſe of further blindnes. Yea, if the blinde lead the blinde, the ignorant idolater take vpon him to teache the ignorant people of lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time broght vp in idolatrie: neither of bothe can eſcape condemnation ſo long as they follow that traine. And therefore it wil nothing vnbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my Lordes conſcience albeit that after his negligence and lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce he begin to cry to ſuche as he tearmes his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ock, bewar of fals prophetes. For it may be that him ſelf be one of that no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. Yea, perchance the falſeſt that they haue harde this hundreth year.<note place="margin">Duet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </note> For if he be a fals Prophet that teacheth men to follow ſtrange Gods, that prophecies a lie in the name of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Iere. 14</note> and ſpeaketh to the people the diuination and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat of his own hart,<note place="margin">Iere. 18</note> that cauſeth the people to erre, and leaue the old pathes, and to walke in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174733:17"/>
the pathe of the way that is not troden. That conſtantlie ſay to them that haue prouoked God to angre. The Lorde heath ſpoken it. Ye ſhall haue peace. And to all that walk after the luſtes of there own hartes there ſhal no euil chance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. &amp;c. If finally,<note place="margin">Iere. 23.</note> they be fals prophetes that be auaricious and ſtudie for adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, that ſowe pilloues vnder the arme hoilles of wicked men, and lay ſinners a ſleap,<note place="margin">Ezeh. 13.</note> and promes life to them, to whome they oght not to promes it. If theſe be fals prophetes (I ſay) as the Scripture effirmeth them to be, then ſtandeth my Lorde abbote in a wonderous perplexitie and ſuche as beleue him, in no les danger.</p>
                        <p>For God hath neuer pronunced, ſuche artickles as my Lorde calleth holſome doctrine, the chief of them, to wit, the maſſe, purgatorie, praying to ſainctes, erecting of images &amp; ſuche other, haue no aſſurance of Gods worde, but are the meare dreames, ſtatutes, and inuentions of men, as there particuler examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (if my Lord pleaſeth to abyde the tryal) wil more plainlie witnes, &amp; therefore, it is no ſufficient aſſurance to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the auditure, that my Lord burden his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, in the preſence of God that his artick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les be godly, neceſſar, &amp; expedient to be beleued. For ſo haue euer the fals Prophetes done, when they &amp; there doctrine, was impugned. Did not the prophetes and preaſts of Baal affirme there doctrine &amp; religion to be godlie, againſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Elias?<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18</note> They did not onely burden there conſcience, but alſo offred them ſelues, to ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:174733:18"/>
tryal (God him ſelf being iudge) before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King and before the whole people.<note place="margin">
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. Ac. 22</note> The ſelf ſame thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g did the fals prophetes againſt Micheas and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie, and therefore yet againe I ſay my Lords conſcience (if a blind zeal be worthy of the name of conſcience) will neither ſaue him ſelf nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe it is not grounded vpon God, his reueilled wil nor promes. If my Lorde thinketh that the holy catholick Church is ſufficient aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for his conſcience, let him vnderſtand that the ſame buckler had the fals prophetes againſt Ieremie for they cryed,<note place="margin">Iere. 7.</note> the temple of the Lorde the temple of the Lorde, the temple of the Lord, but as he with one ſtroke did bruſt their buckler a ſonder, ſaying put not your truſt in leing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: ſo ſay we that how catholick (that is vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal) that euer their Churche hath bene, holy are they neuer able to proue it, neither in lyfe, making of lawes, nor in ſoundnes of doctrine, as in my anſwer giuen by mouth, I haue more pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely ſhewen. It pleaſeth my Lorde to terme vs, wicked and deceatful preachers, who go about not knowing wherefro we come, nor by what ordoure, &amp; further he feareth not to pronu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce our doctrine, fals wicked, and vngodlie, for of vs, &amp; our doctrine it is plane that my Lorde ment and meneth.</p>
                        <p>I anſwer that as by Gods worde, we accuſe the whole maſſe of mannes nature, of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and wickednes, ſo do we not flatter our ſelues, but willingly confeſſe ourſelues ſo ſubiect to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and naturall wickednes, that the good
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174733:18"/>
that we wold do, we do it not, but the euill that we hate, that we do. Yea, we do not deny but that in our liues and outward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation there be many things bothe worthie of reformation and reprehenſion. But yet if our liues ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the liues of them, that accuſeth vs, be it in general or be it in particular, we doubt not to be iuſtified, bothe before, God and man. For how many miniſters this day within ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, is my Lorde abbote (ioyning with him the whole rable of the horned Biſchoopes) able to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict to be adulterers, fornicators, dronckards, bloodſcheders, opperſſors of the poore wedow, fatherles, or ſtranger, or yet, that do idilly liue vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweat of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes browes. And how many of them from the hieſt to the loweſt, are able to abyde an aſſyſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed crimes. And yet ſhal we be called by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wicked and deceatful preachers, euen as if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrongeſt &amp; moſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune harlot, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer wes knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bordell, ſhould ſcl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander &amp; reuile an honeſt &amp; pudick matro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But in ſomwhat muſt the ſonnes reſemble there father.</p>
                        <p>The deuil as that he is perpetuall enimie to treuth and to ane honeſt life, ſo is he a lear and accuſar of our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and therefore albeit ſuche as ſerue him in idolatrie and all filthines of life, ſpew out againſt vs, there wennome and leis, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> teſtimonie of a good conſcience, we refer ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance to him, to whome it aperteineth, neither yet wold we haue ones opened our mouthes for the defence of our owne innocencie (for God be praiſed, euen before the world it will vtter the
<pb facs="tcp:174733:19"/>
ſelf, war not that in ſclandring our liues, they go about, to deface the glorious goſpel of Ieſus Chriſte, whereof it hath pleaſed his mercie to make vs miniſters: and in that eace, let them be aſſured, that the lies which without ſhame &amp; aſſurance, they cauſies womet out againſt vs, with ſhame and double confucion they ſhal iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie receaue againe in there owne boſomes. If my Lorde abbote alledge, that he accuſeth not our liues and external conuerſation, but our doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine which he termes fals, wicked, and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, we anſwer, that as that doeth more greiue vs, nor the ſclandring of our liues, ſo doubt we nothing, but that he that made his fauorable ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, to afflicted Ieruſalem in theſe wordes:</p>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Iſay. 14.</note>All inſtrument that is prepared againſt thee, ſhal not proſper, and euerie toung, that ſhal riſe againſt thee in iudgement, thou ſhalt rightlie conuict and condeme of impietie. We doubt not (I ſay) but the ſame God, will in this our age, confound the tounges, that oppone them ſelues to his eternal veritie, which is the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and aſſurance of our doctrine. And therefore we nothing feare to ſay, that my Lorde in the end ſhal ſpead no better (if he continew, in that his irreuerent rayling) then ſuche as heretofore, haue blaſphemed Ieſus Chriſte, and his eternall veritie, to the which albeit for the preſent, they wil not be ſubiect, and that becauſe our perſones and preſence whome God maketh miniſters of the ſame, are contemptible and deſpyſed, yet in the end, they ſhal feal, that in rebelling againſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174733:19"/>
our admonicions, they were rebellious to the mouth of God, and in defaſing vs, they haue diſpyſed, the eternal Sonne of God, who of his mercie, hath ſent vs, to rebuke there impeitie, and to reduce to knowledge, and vnto the true pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor againe, ſuche, as through blind ignorance, haue followed the inuentions, and dreames of men: and haue ſoght iuſtice, remiſſion of ſinnes, and reconciliation with God, by other meanes then by Ieſus Chriſte, and by true faith in his blood. But of this point, I knowe my Lorde moſte doubtes, To wit, whether God hath ſent vs, or not? For my Lorde ſayes we go about, not knowing wherefro we come, nor by what ordor, we anſwer, that in our conſciences we knowe, and he him ſelf, wil beare vs record, that we are not ſent by that Romane Antichriſte, whome he calleth Pope, nor yet from his carnal Cardinal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, nor dum horned Biſchoppes: and thereof we reioyſe, Being aſſured, that as we are not ſent by Chriſtes manifeſt enimie in the earth, ſo are we ſent by Ieſus Chriſte him ſelf, and that by ſuche ordor, as God hath euer kept, from the beginning, when publick corruption entered in the Church, by ſleuth, and impietie of ſuche, as of duetie oght to haue fedd the flock, and to haue reteaned the people vnder obedience of God, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel in religion, as in life and maners. The ordor of God (I ſay) hath bene in ſuche publick cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, to raiſe vp ſimple, and obſcure men, in the beginning of there vocacion, vnknowen to the worlde: to rebuke the manifeſt defection of
<pb facs="tcp:174733:20"/>
the people from God, to conuict the paſtors of there formar negligence, fleuth, and idolatrie, &amp; to prononce them vnworthie of there offices.</p>
                        <p>
                           <note place="margin">Reg. 17 Iere. 35. Amo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</note>For ſo was Helias ſent in the dayes of Ahab, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie in the time of corruption, vnder Iehoia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, and Zedechias. Amos vnder Ieroboam, and the reſt of the Prophets, euerie one in there own tyme, and after the ſame ordour hath God raſed vp i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe our dayes, ſuche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as my Lord &amp; his faction termes, Heretikes, Schiſmatikes Zuinglians, Lutherians, Oecolampadians, &amp; Caluiniſts. To proue the Pope, to be an Antichr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iſte, his whole glorie in the earth, to be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther repugnant, to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicion of Chriſtes true miniſters. The maſſe to be idolatrie, &amp; a baſtard ſeruice of God, yea more corrupted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer was the Sacrifice in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of the Prophetes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yet they affirmed them to be abominable before God. Purgatorie to be nothing but a pykepurs. The defence of mannes frewill to do good, and auoide euil, to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> damned heriſie of Pelagius. The forbidding of mariage to any eſtate of men or woman, to be the doctrine of Deuills. And the forbidding of meat for conſcience ſaik, to ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cead of the ſame fontaine. The erecting images in Churches, &amp; in publick places of aſſembleis, to be againſt the expreſſed commandement of God. Prayer for the dead, and vnto ſainctes, to be work done without faith, and therefore to be ſinne. Briefly God hath raſed vp men in theſe our dayes, ſo to diſcouer the turpitud and filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of that Babiloniane harlote, that hir werrie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174733:20"/>
golden cuppe, in the which hir fornication wes hid before, is become abhominable to all ſuche, as truſt for the life euerlaſting. And they haue further ſett ſo vehement a fyre in the werray ground of hir glorie, that is, in hir vſurped au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, that ſhe and it, are bothe like to burne, to there vttermoſte confuſion. My Lorde and his companions feare no ſuche threatninges. they are but rayling knaues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſpytfully ſpeak againſt there holy mother the Church. I haue alreadie ſaid that the Prophetes in there dayes wes euen ſo rewarded of thoſe, that had the ſame tytle &amp; dignitie, that now our aduerſaries clame. And yet did they not eſcape the plagues prono<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and in the ſame confidence ſtand we, reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing further, that howſoeuer they repyne, ſtorme and rage, yet they that are of God, hear vs, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we the voice of Ieſus Chriſte ſpeaking in vs his weak inſtruments, and do flie from that horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble harlote, and from hir filthynes, which is to vs a ſufficient aſſurance that God hath ſent vs for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of his choſen. But my Lorde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance requireth miracles, to proue our laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vocation. For ſo doeth Vinzet procutor for the Papiſtes. To bothe I anſwer, that a treuth by it ſelf without myracles, hath ſufficient ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gth to proue the laughful vocation of the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof, but miracles deſtitute of treuth, haue efficacie to deceaue, but neuer to bring to God. But this by the grace of God ſhalbe more fully entreated, in the anſwer to Vinzetes que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiones therevpon. And yet one word man I ſay
<pb facs="tcp:174733:21"/>
before I make end, to my Lorde, and vnto the reſt of the Popes creatures. And it is this? If they will ſtudie to keap them ſelues, in credeit &amp; eſtimation, let them neuer call our vocation in doubt, for we in continent will obiect to them, that from the moſte to the leaſt, there is none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongs them, laughfully called, to ſerue within the Church of God. But all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ſymonie, all are heretykes, all receaue the ſpirit of lies, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leproſie of Gehezi, and finally, being accuſed in there firſt ordination, they neither can giue gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, nor benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the people of God, and this by there own law I offer my ſelf to proue, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidentlie as my Lords Biſchops, abbots, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, and the reſt of that ſect, are able to proue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, called to eccleſiaſticall function (as they terme it) by there fathers bulles, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Pope. I wonder not a lytil, that my Lorde ſhould alledge, that I wes certified that he might not be preſent at Kirkoſwald, the day that firſt I offred my ſelf to reſiſt his vaine and blaſphemous artickles. I am able to proue that by his promes he had bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d himſelf ofter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ones to be preſent. And alſo that by famous gentle men that ſame Sonday in the morning he was required either to come and teach according to his promes, and ſo to ſuffer his doctrine in audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of ſuche as he named his owne flock, to be tryed, or els, to come and heare doctrine, &amp; with ſobrietie and gentilnes, to oppon at his pleaſure. Theſe two heades (I ſay) I am able to proue. But that I wes certified, that he could not be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174733:21"/>
preſent. &amp;c. I think it ſhalbe as hard to proue, as to proue that Melchiſedec, made Sacrifice of bread, and wine vnto God. But my Lorde ſhall haue libertie of me, to alledge in ſuche caſes what pleaſeth him, ſo long as his allegation ſhal not preiudge the veritie, nor giue patrocynie to a lie, in maters of religion. It is not of great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whether I was certified, or not, that my Lorde could not be preſent, as he alledgeth. I preſented my ſelf at the day appointed. And that is ſome argument, that I greatlie feared not my Lordes preſence. The letters that haue paſſed betuix vs, together withſome anſwers, that I differed, ſhalbe put in regiſter before the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. That men may ſee, the whole procedings of bothe parties. And this muche by writ, to my Lordes firſt oration giuen in, in writ.</p>
                        <p>Now followeth my anſwer, to the reſt, giuen at that ſame inſtant by mouth.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="dialogue">
                        <sp>
                           <stage>Iohn Knox anſwereth by mouth</stage>
                           <p>BEcauſe I perceaue, bothe in your proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and artickle, that ye diſpute not vpon theſe maters, as diſputable, but as of things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie concluded, by the Kirk, general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelles, and doctors: I muſt ſay ſomwhat in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, how farre I will admit of any of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named.<note place="margin">Ephe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>.</note> And of the Kirk firſt (I ſay) that I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it to be the ſpous of Chriſts Ieſus, builded vpon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets: ſo that into all doctrine, it heareth
<pb facs="tcp:174733:22"/>
the voice of the ſpous onelie, and an ſtranger, it will not heare,<note place="margin">Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>0</note> according to the wordes of our maſter Chriſt Ieſus. My ſhepe heare my voice. &amp;c. And therefore if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any multitude, vnder the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Kirk, will obtrude, vnto vs, any doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine neceſſar to be beleued to our ſaluation, and bringeth not for the ſame, the expres worde of Ieſus Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, &amp;c. men muſt aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done me, althogh I acknowledge it not to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kirk of God, for the reaſon foreſaid. And vnto the generall counſelles, I anſwer the ſame, to wit, that ſuche as hath bene gathered duelie &amp; in the name of God, for extirpatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hereſies, with my whole harte I do reuerence. Prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, that the doctrine, that they propone to be beleued, haue the approbation of the plaine worde of God, or els with that ancient I muſt ſay, that more credit is to be giuen to an man, bringing for him,<note place="margin">Panor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mita.</note> the teſtimonie of Gods Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, then to an generall counſell, affirming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doctrine without the ſame. And as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the authoritie of the doctors (for whome I prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe my God, as that I do for all them whome he maketh profitable inſtrumentes in his kirk) I think my Lorde,<note place="margin">Let the godlie iudge if theſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticions be reaſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable.</note> will bind me no ſtraiter, then he hath deſyred to be bound him ſelf, that is, that men be not receaued, as God. And therefore with Aguſtine I conſent, that whatſoeuer the doctors propone, and plamly confirme the ſame by the euident teſtimonie of the Scriptures, I am hartlie content to receaue the ſame, but els, that it be laughful to me with, Ierome to ſay,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174733:22"/>
whatſoeuer is affirmed, without the authoritie of Gods Scriptures, with the ſame facilitie it may be reiected, as it is affirmed. And theſe thre admitted. So forth I enter in diſputation.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Thair ar diuers heides quhair with I am of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, willing that the purpoſe we come for, may go ſhortlie to paſſe. Thairfore preſentlie I will omitt. And as the occaſion ſall ſerue of the doctoures, counſalles and ocht elles, quhilkis ar not expreſly contened in the Scriptures. And this quicklie go to the purpoſe.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox</speaker>
                           <p>Ye are not ignorant (my Lorde) that in euerie diſputation, the ground oght ſo to be laide, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mater diſputable, or the queſtion, either come vnder an perfite definicion, or els vnder an ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient diſcription: and ſpecially when the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, De woce ſimplici. As is, Miſſa. Yf it ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſe your Lordſchip to defyne the maſſe, or yet ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficientlie to diſcriue it, I will take occaſion of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which I think wrong. And if not, then muſt I explaine my minde, what maſſe it is, that I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to impung, and haue called idolatrie, not the bliſſed inſtitution of the Lorde Ieſus, which he hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to be vſed in his kirk,<note place="margin">Let men iudge if this be not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the papiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal meſſe</note> to his gaincomi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, but that which is cropen in, into the kirk viſible, without all approbation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of God. And this maſſe, I ſay, hath a name, a forme and action, an opinion conceaued of it, and an actor of the ſame. And vnto the whole foure I ſay, that neither the name, the forme and
<pb facs="tcp:174733:23"/>
action, nor the opinion, nor actor, haue there aſſurance of Gods plaine worde.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>As to the diffinicion or deſcription that I gaif the laſt ȝeir, I will abyde at it this ȝeir, for I am not cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>min in vſe of eſt, &amp; non eſt. And as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe that he wil impung, or any mannes maſſe, ȝea, and it war the paipes awin meſſe, I will mantein nathing but Ieſus Chriſtes meſſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to my artickle as it is writtin, and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition contened in my buik, quhilk he hes taine on hand to impung.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>As I can conceaue, my Lordes anſwer, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teineth thre heades, the firſt is, a relation to his booke as conteaning the difinicion of the maſſe. The ſecond a declaration of his Lordſchipes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie.<note place="margin">Let men iudge how fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable the ſone is vnto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> And the third, an affirmation, that he wil affirme no maſſe, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe of Ieſus Chriſt, yea, not if it wer the popes owne maſſe. Vnto the firſt I anſwer. That I haue not red his Lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchipes booke (not excuſing thereintill my own negligence) and therefore it appeareth vnto me, that rather his Lordſhip, ſhould cauſe the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to be red out of his booke, nor to burden me with the ſeaking of it. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipes conſtancie, I beſeak the eternal God, to make vs all conſtant, in his eternal veritie: for inconſtancie in the treuth, can not lack infamie, and great danger. But to me it appeareth, that in no wyſe it can hurt, the fame, nor conſcience of the godlie, to confeſſe them ſelues men, who
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174733:23"/>
bothe may erre, and alſo be occation that others erre. And yet, when that the fuller knowledge commeth vnto them, by the ſpirit of God, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oght to impute vnto them inconſtancie, albeit they retreat there formar error, as in diuers hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des did that learned Auguſtine. But the thride head doeth moſte delite me, to wit, that my lord hath affirmed that he will defend no maſſe, but the maſſe of the Lorde Ieſus:<note place="margin">Note my offer</note> which if his lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will performe (as my good hope is) then I dout not, but we are on the werray point of an chriſtiane aggrement. For whatſoeuer his lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchip ſhall proue to me, to be done by the Lorde Ieſus, that, without all contradiction, I ſhall embrace. Prouiding that his lordſhip alledge nothing to be done, by Ieſus Chriſte, which his owne inſtitution, witneſſeth not to be done.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>I define the meſſe, as concerning the ſubſtance, and effect, to be the ſacrifice and oblation, of the Lordes bodie and blude, geuen and offered by him, in the latter Supper. And takis the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, to my warrand, according to my artickle as it is written. And for the firſt confirmation of the ſame, groundes me vpon the ſacrifice and oblation of Melchiſedec. To the ſecond, I thank Iohn Knox of his praſe and prayer of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, and in lyk maner for chriſtiane cheriteis ſaik, praſe God with all my hart, for his indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retnes and pertinacitie (gif ſwa be that he be in error) and will wiſh him, that he be willed to refuſe his pertinacitie, as I ſall do my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancie
<pb facs="tcp:174733:24"/>
gif I be in error. To the thrid, for auoiding of cauillation, I mein that I will defend no meſſe as concerning the ſubſtance, inſtitution &amp; effect, bot that meſſe onelie, quhilk is inſtitut be Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox</speaker>
                           <p>Omitting to further conſideration, the anſwer to the definition, to the laſt two heades I ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie anſwer, that I praiſed no conſtancie, but that which is in the treuth. And as touching my ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en indurednes, wherewith my Lorde ſeameth to burden me, I plainlie proteſt before God, that if I knew my ſelf in error, in that cace, or in any other, that concerneth the doctrine of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: I ſhould not be aſhamed, publictlie to confeſſe it. But the laſt parte of my Lordes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, appeareth ſomparte to varie (in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) from his formar affirmation, which I tooke to be, that his lordſhip wold defend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe, which he was not able to proue, to be the verray inſtitution of Ieſus Chriſte. And therefore, muſt I haue recourſe, vnto the formar diuiſion of the maſſe: which is in name, action, opinion, &amp; actor. And humblie requireth of his lordſhip, that he wold ſignifie vnto me, if he wold be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to proue the name to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by Ieſus Chrſte:<note place="margin">Note if this be to ſhoot an piſtollet at the meſſe.</note> the whole action and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies from beginning, to the end, to be the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of almightie God. The opinion, which hath bene conceaued, taught, and written of it, for to be aggreable with the Scripturs of God. And finally, if that the actor, hath his aſſurance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174733:24"/>
of God, to do that, which he there publictlie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth, he doeth.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>As willing that the treuth cum to ane tryall, I will not trifle, bot ſchortlie geues for anſwer.<note place="margin">A ſhifti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g anſwer.</note> I wil begin at the beſt firſt, quhilk is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſtance and effect. And as to the ceremonies, actor and name, ſal defend them abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantlie (Godwilling) conform to my artickle quhen I cum thairto.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>The ceremonies vſed in the maſſe, and the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion conceaued of the ſame, haue bene holden ſubſtanciall partes thereof,<note place="margin">Let the papeſts anſwer if this be trew or not.</note> into the conſcience of a great multitude. And therefore, oght the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the weak, and infirme, firſt to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from that bondage. For what my Lorde affirmeth of the maſſe (to wit, that it is a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice) this perchance may be alſo alledged to apar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teane to the right inſtitution of Ieſus Chriſte, in ſome cace, which ones wes woid, bothe of thoſe ceremonies, and that damnable opinion.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>I am not cumin heir to mantein the opiniones of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to defend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtitution of Ieſus Chriſt, conform to my artickle.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>It appeareh to me yet againe,<note place="margin">This is a dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt the meſſe.</note> that my Lorde is willing to defend no thing, but the werray inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt Ieſus. And I haue alreadie affirmed, that neither the name of the maſſe, the ceremonies vſed in the ſame, the opinion concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of it, neither yet that power, which the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb facs="tcp:174733:25"/>
vſurneth, hath either the inſtitution or aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>I am willing to defend my diffinition concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the meſſe, as I haue diffined it, and takes Goddes word to my warrand,<note place="margin">My lord fled the Barras for the firſt.</note> and as to the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies actor and all the reſt fall defend God willing to be aggreable with Goddes word all throuch abundantlie as tyme and place ſal ſerue beginning firſt at the ſubſtance and effect.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>I anſwer, that albeit in my iudgement, the conſcience of man, oght firſt to haue bene ſett at libertie, yet hoping that my Lorde wilbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, according to his promes, that the name, ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and the reſt of the accidents of the maſſe ſuffer the tryal by the worde of God. I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſhortlie to enter in the bodie of the mater.</p>
                           <p>And deſireth the difinition to be reſumed.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <note place="margin">Let my Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</note>I promes, before this honorable auditor, to defend that all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tened in the action of the meſſe to be aggreable with Goddes word, prouiding alwayes we gang to the ſubſtance.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <p>The difinition being reſumed.</p>
                        <sp>
                           <stage>Iohn Knox anſwered.</stage>
                           <p>Your lordſhip is not ignorant, that in euerie difinition, there oght to be, Genus, which I take your lordſhip here maketh this term (Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium) but becauſe the term is generall, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scriptures of God is diuerſly taken, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it muſt be broght to a certane kinde. For in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174733:25"/>
the Scriptures there be ſacrifices called EVCHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RISTICA that is, of thankes giuing. The mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of our bodies, and the obedience that we giue to God, in the ſame, is alſo called Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Prayer &amp; inuocation of the name of God hath alſo the ſame name within the Scriptures. Liberalitie toward the poore, is alſo ſo termed. But there is one Sacrifice, which is greateſt, and moſte of all, called, Propiciatorium, which is that Sacrifice, whereby, ſatiſfaction is made to the iuſtice of God, being offended at the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of man. &amp;c. Now I deſire of my Lord that he appoint vnto the maſſe, whiche of theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices beſt pleaſeth him.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Quhat ȝe mein be the Sacrifice, Propiciatorium, preſentlie I will not diſpute. But I tak the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice vpon the cro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>, to be the onelie Sacrifice of redemption, and the Sacrifice of the maſſe, to be the Sacrifice of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoration, of Chriſts death and paſſion.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>So farre as I can conceaue of my Lordes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, he maketh no Sacrifice, Propiciatorie,<note place="margin">Heir are mo can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one.</note> in the meſſe: which is the chiefhead, which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to impung. For, as for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoration of Chriſtes death and paſſion, that I grant, and publictlie do confeſſe, to be celebrat in the right vſe of the Lordes S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>pper, which I denie the meſſe to be.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>It is ȝour deutie according to formall procei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb facs="tcp:174733:26"/>
to impung my warrand,<note place="margin">If this be ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or not let men iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dge.</note> quhilk I haue choſen, to defend my diffinition be, and artickle euen as it is writtin.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Proteſting that this mekle is win, that the Sacrifice of the maſſe, being denied by me to be a Sacrifice Propiciatorie for the ſinnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quick and the dead,<note place="margin">Let men now iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the meſſe gat a wond or not.</note> according to the opinion thereof before conceaued, hath no patron, at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: I am content to procede.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>I proteſt that he hes win nothing of me as ȝit, and referres it, to black and quhite, contened in our writing.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>I haue openlie denied the maſſe to be an Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice Propiciatorie for the quick.<note place="margin">Note.</note> &amp;c. and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence thereof is denied. And therefore I referre me vnto the ſame iudges that my Lorde hath clamed.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Ȝe may deny quhat ȝe pleis, for all that ȝe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny I tak not preſentlie to impung, bot quhair I began thair wil I end,<note place="margin">Shift on</note> that is, to defend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meſſe, conforme to my artickle.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Seing that neither the name, the action, the opinion, nor the actor of the maſſe, can be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for this preſent, I wold glaidly knowe what I ſhould impung.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>All aboue rehearſed can be defended, and ſalbe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174733:26"/>
defended (Godwilling),<note place="margin">I did no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing but as my lord comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</note> and quhair ȝe are glaid to knaw, quhat ȝe ſould impung, apperanlie that ſould be na newinges to ȝow, for I certifie ȝow ȝe ſould impung my warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alledged for defence of my diffinition and artickle.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>If be your warrand,<note place="margin">Haue at your gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>und.</note> ye vnderſtand the obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made in bread and wine by Melchiſedec, I plainly deny, that Melchiſedec made any oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Sacrifice, of bread and wine vnto God, and deſires the text to be iudge.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>It is ȝour pairt to impung, and myne to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, for I am the defender, and ſalbe Godwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Can I impung more plane, then when I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie your ground?</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>I ſay the denying of the ground is na proper impugnation.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Your lordſhips ground is, that Melchiſedec is the figure of Chriſte, in that,<note place="margin">Let men iudge now if my lords ground for the meſſe be not ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> that he did offer vnto God bread and wine, and therefore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houed Ieſus Chriſte to offer in his latter ſupper his bodie and blood, vnder the formes of bread and wine. I anſwer to your ground, yet againe, that Melchiſedec offered neither bread nor wine vnto God. And therefore it, that ye wold there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon conclude hath no aſſurance of your grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <pb facs="tcp:174733:27"/>Preue that.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Whether that the probatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a negatiue, ſhould be deuolued vpon me, eſpecially when I haue denied your chief ground, I am content the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arned iudge.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Moued throuch feruor of the tryall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treuth of Goddes worde, I refuſe logik captious ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillationis for the preſent (not perchance for ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance) bot y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we tyne not tyme,<note place="margin">Gather what is ſpoken.</note> to finniſh and eſtablis our godlie pretence for the eaſe and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes of the conſcience of the noble men heir pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>I haue els proteſted, that I abhor all cauilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones, and yet againe declares vnto your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that in my iudgement it is the way moſte ſuccinct, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your lordſhip proue your own grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that is, that Melchiſedec, offered vnto God bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad and wine, which I denie.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>I tak the text to be my warrand and ground.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>The text being red, the 14. of Geneſis. There is no mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made of any oblation of bread and wine, made by Melchiſedec vnto God, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Melchiſedec being King of Salem,<note place="margin">Gen. 14.</note> broght forth bread and wine. And that being Prieſt of the moſte hie God, he bleſſed Abraham as the text beareth witnes. And therefore I ſay that the text, preueth not that any oblation of bread
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:174733:27"/>
and wine, was made vnto God by Melchiſedec.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Ȝe do affirm that Melchiſedec brocht furth bread and wine. I ſpeir at ȝow to what effect?<note place="margin">Iudge now if my lord ſhiftes.</note>
                           </p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Will ye deuolue vpon me now, the perſone of an anſwerer, ſeing that ye refuſed your ſelf of before the ſame?</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>This quhilk he calles anſwering, is mair ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlie to be called impungnation in this cace,<note place="margin">Marck what is confeſſed by my lord.</note> in that, finding the text to ſerue nothing for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is plaine impungnation to my pretence.</p>
                           <p>And ſwa are ȝe cled rather with the perſonage of ane impungnar, nor ane defendar.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Whether that I ſuſteane the perſonage of an impungner, or of an defender, I am not bound to anſwer, what wes done with the bread and wine, after that it was broght forth. It ſuffiſeth to me for my formar purpoſe, that there is no mention made in the text, that bread and wine by Melchiſedec was offered vnto God.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>It ryndes to ȝow to preif,<note place="margin">Let the learned Iudge if this be trew.</note> that Melchiſedec made no oblation of bread and wine vnto God.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>It ſuffiſeth to me, that in the text there is no mention made that Melchiſedec, made any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of bread and wine vnto God, as ye before alledged, and hath laide for your ground.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <pb facs="tcp:174733:28"/>I ſay the wordes of the text ar plain that Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec maid oblation of bread and wine vnto God,<note place="margin">Note if ſo be.</note> and deſires ȝow to impreue the ſame be the text.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>My inprobation is alreadie ledd. For in the text there is no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of oblation of bread and wine made vnto God. And therefore I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, that the whole world iudge, whether the ground be not ſufficientlie inprouen or not.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Melchiſedec brocht furth bread and wine, quhilk he did not without cauſe, and ȝe deny yat he brocht it furth,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider in what ſtraitnes my lord was now,</note> for the cauſe, that I alledge, ergo, for ſome other cauſe. Quhilk gif ȝe wil not, nor can not ſhaw preſentlie, I ſall do deligence to cauſe the preſent auditor vnderſtand cleirly, that he brocht furth bread and wine for the cauſe alledged be me. Prouiding that gif ȝe will not ſhaw the cauſe preſently, that ȝe ſal haue no pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to ſhaw it heirefter.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>I anſwer, that he broght forth bread &amp; wine, the text plainly affirmeth, and I haue alreadie granted. But that he made oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame, becauſe the text ꝑporteth it not, I can not gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it. As touching the cauſe wherefore he broght it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th (if place ſhal be giuen to coniectors, and that not grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded without great probabilitie, and alſo with ſufrage of ſome of the ancients, to wit, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus &amp; Chryſoſtom.) It may be ſaid that Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec being an King, broght forth bread and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174733:28"/>
wine, to refreſh Abraham and his werie ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors. And this, for your ſatiſfaction of the cauſe, why he broght forth bread and wine: euer ſtill ſticking vpon the principal grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. That becauſe no mention is made, that Melchiſedec made ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of bread and wine vnto God, I deny it, as of before.</p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                     <div type="dialogue">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>The pennult of September. 1562.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Of Iohn Knox ſaying is aboue reheirſed, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue twa heides in ſpecial, the ane is,<note place="margin">This was the beginni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng of the ſecond dayes trauell after that my lord had ſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</note> that Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec maid na oblation vnto God, dot he did bring furth the bread and wine, to refreſh Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and his companie. I will anſwer vnto the ſaides heides formally, and on this maner. Firſt I wil mak impugnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ye laſt heid quhair it is thocht that he did refreſh Abraham and his companie. In that the text is manifeſt in ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trar, in ſa far as the text teſtifies, that Abraham and his company war refreſhed be the ſpolȝe of the enimies, and was not refreſhed,<note place="margin">Let my Lordes argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be noted</note> nor miſtered na refreſhing of Melchiſedec, quhairfore it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that Melchiſedec brocht furth bread and wine vnto ane vther effect, nor to refreſh Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and his companie.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>My formar proue, that Melchiſedec, did not offer bread and wine vnto God, ſtandeth vpon this ground, that the text maketh mention of no maner oblation made there vnto God of bread and wine. And therefore in a mater of ſo great importance, darre not I affirme oblation to be
<pb facs="tcp:174733:29"/>
made, whill that the holy Ghoſt kepeth ſilence. And now vnto my Lordes argument,<note place="margin">Anſwer to the formar argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</note> firſt, I anſwer, that there is no contradiction betuix theſe two, Abraham and his company, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed of the ſpoolies of there enimies: and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham and his company were refreſhed of the liberalitie of Melchiſedec. And firſt, becauſe in the tyme when Abraham and his company re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued there nouriſhement of the ſubſtance of there enimies, they were out of the preſence of Melchiſedec: and not returned vnto there cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. But albeit that they had bene euen in the preſence of Melchiſedec, yet they might haue bene nouriſhed, partlie be his liberalitie, and partlie be there owne prouiſion. And thridly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the text doeth not affirme that Abraham and his, wer nouriſhed onely of the ſpoile. I can not admit my Lordes argument.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>For ſatiſfaction of the auditoure, and to cum quicklie to the point without drifting of tyme I will refuſe reaſoning, after ſcoolmaner, and will go ȝit to the text, and depend thairupon. And on this maner ſayaud (Saif onely that, quhilk the ȝong men hes eatin) I inferr of this text, that it dois appeir, ȝe and is manifeſt, that thair rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mair nor was eitin, be Abraham and his company, for the preſent.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>I do not deny, but there remaned ſubſtance, which wes neither eatin nor conſumed by Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and his company, but what ſhalbe hereof
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174733:29"/>
concluded?</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>I infer yat not onely thair remaned ſubſtance, bot thair remaned mekle mair ſubſtance, nor A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham and his company was able to conſume, ȝea, and to gif ane great deale away, for quhy, Abraham was victor of foure Kingis, quhair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throuch he obtened ane great ſpolȝe, &amp; not onely of foure, bot alſo he gat the ſpolȝe of vther fyue, and gat all thair viuers and meat, quhairthrouch it is manifeſt be ye verray plaine text that Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and his company, had mekle mair meat nor they war able to conſume, and ſwa miſtered he nor his company na refreſching of Melchiſedec, conſidering he and his company was bot ane meine nomber (as I wold ſay) thre hundreth &amp; auchtene.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>The victorie of Abraham is in the text ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as alſo the nomber of the Kinges vainque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. And that there remaned ſubſtance, yea, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle more then was ſpent; I do not deny. But this wil not neceſſarlie conclude, but that Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec of his liberalitie broght forth bread and wine, to the purpoſe forſaid: as be coniecture, is moſte probable. For men of godlines and ciuill honeſtie, do not onely ſhaw them ſelues, liberal in tyme of extreme neceſſitie, but alſo wil declair there beneuolence without great neid, yea, and in greateſt aboundance.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Becauſe Iohn Knox ſpeakis of ſubſtance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differentlie,
<pb facs="tcp:174733:30"/>
I will deſire him to declair his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, conforme to the text, quhither Abraham and his company, recouered of the nyne Kingis ſpolȝeis bread and wine, and vther ſuſtenance, quhilk treulie, albeit the text do not proport the ſame in plaine wordes, ȝit can na man of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment think vtherwiſe, as I can gif many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth examples in the Scriptures, and ane in ſpeciall, quhair Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde ſpeakis in his awin prayer, called the Pater noſter, of day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bread, quhairinto is to be vnderſtand all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired vnto the ſuſtentation of man, albeit the text dois not expreſly declair the ſamin.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>I haue ſpoken of ſubſtance in generall, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by the plaine text, which maketh men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion neither of bread nor wine, in expreſſed wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, other nor of that which Melchiſedec broght forth. And by all apperance, there could not any great ſtore, of bread and wine be caried back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, by Abraham and his company, after the victorie of his enimies. For plaine it is, that he broght nothing back, which they before did not carie away (him ſelf and his company onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) we read that they toke the pray of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Gomorra, and caried with them the ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Let this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iectur ſerue for anſwer to my lords ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumemt</note> yea, &amp; the victual, Loth, his ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. &amp;c. Now albeit that in the beginning there vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualles had bene great, yet being ſuche a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as we may iuſtlie ſuppoſe them to haue bene: and alſo being arriued within there own coſtes, it is not appeari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that great ſtore wes reſerued.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174733:30"/>
But howſoeuer it be, this mater ſtanding in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture, we wil of neceſſitie conclud no thing, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the holie Ghoſt hath not expreſſed it. As touching my Lordes allegation, of the daylie bread. &amp;c. I acknowledge with his lordſchip that to be the familiar phraſe of the Scripture, that vnder the name of bread, is commonly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken all thinges neceſſar for the vſe of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, like as theſe, Frange efurienti panem tuum. &amp;c.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Hauand conſideration, that Iohn Knox, wald caſt in ane ſuſpicion in the hartes of the honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble auditor (ſaifand his pardone) be continual repeticion of this word coniecture, we wil do as God will giue vs grace, to tak this policie out of the hartes of the auditor, and that by proper diſcription of argumentes of inferrence or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture, quhairfore the auditor ſall conſider, that thair is ſum conietures and argumentes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce quhilk neceſſarlie concludes and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es vpon.<note place="margin">Let the learned conſider this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cription of coniec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tural ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts whiche do neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</note> And arcalled nottheles argumentes of coniecture or inferrence, becauſe the ane worde is not the other, nor dois not expreſly conclud the other, as for ane familiar example, Spirat, ergo viuit, as I wald ſay, he aindes ergo he liues. Quhairfore I infer that this conference of phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, or maner of ſpeach quhair it is ſaid in the text, al thair victuallis, neceſſarly inferris breid wine, and all vther thingis expedient to be eatin, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thair was great aboundance in the cite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is quhilk war ſpolȝeit as do this phraſe, break vnto the hungrie thy bread, and ſwa quhatſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb facs="tcp:174733:31"/>
may be inferred of the ane phraſe, neceſſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie may be inferred of the vther.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Hitherto I haue trauelled, to make difference betuix that, that man of neceſſitie is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, and that which man may either beleue, or not beleue, without any hurt of conſcience.</p>
                           <p>What God in expreſſed wordes and ſentences, hath committed to vs within the Scriptures &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded the ſame to be beleued, he requireth of vs that neceſſarlie we beleue the ſame. But where the ſpirit of God hath keped ſilence, and hath not in plaine ſentences, declared vnto vs the will of God our Father, there may a man ſuſpend his iudgement, without hurt of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yea, and more ſure it is, not bouldlie to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that which is keped cloſe, by the wiſdome of God: then that we ſhould raſhelie affirme any thing, without the warrand of Gods worde as we are taught by the admonition of Auguſtine. As touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuerſitie of arguments. I know bothe the ſtrength of them, that are called Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſario Concludentia, and of thoſe whiche ſtand in probabilitie,<note place="margin">The grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of fayth is the word of God reuealed</note> which bothe I grant to haue the ſtrength in perſuaſion: but the faith of man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth a ſurer ground, then any argument that can be deduced from nature (to wit) it requireth hearing, and that hearing of the worde of God, according to the doctrine of the Apoſtle. Now to my Lordes argument, I ſay it doeth not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarlie conclude, that Abraham and his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors broght more reddie meat, ſuche as bread and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174733:31"/>
wine back from there victorie, then they were able to ſpend, albeit that they caried with them the whole ſubſtance, yea,<note place="margin">That is the Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gs vicuſt by Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham</note> the whole victualles of Sodom and Gomorra. &amp;c. Becauſe that in the iorney ſome might haue bene loſſed, in the iorney no dout but muche wes ſpent, and in the victorie the reſt might haue bene diſperſed or loſt. For by all apperance Abraham had ſmal reſpect to bread &amp; wine,<note place="margin">Let the reader aduert.</note> more then to that which might reaſonablie ſuſteane him and his company vnto there returne. And thus from coniecture we ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually pas to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture, onles that my Lord be able to proue, that the text affirmeth in plane wordes, that ſuche ſuperflouous aboundance of bread and wine wes broght back, vnto the time that Melchiſedec met him (&amp; althogh his Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dſhip be able ſo to do as I am aſſured no man is able) yet ſhal alwayes Melchiſedec and his libiralitie ſtand ſtill vnconuicted.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>To meit all the heides co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tened in Iohn Knox, partickle aboue rehearſed, notwithſtandinge appearanlie I am conſtrained to the ſame. Ȝit alwayes in fauoris of the auditure,<note place="margin">Let the indiffir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t iudge</note> I will go ſchortlie to ſum ſpeciall heides. And firſt quhair he makes ane meine, that I go by naturall reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonis to perſuade, to take the ſuſpicion of men iuſtly of me in this heid, I ſay and do affirme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue done not in that cauſe as ȝit, bot co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forme to the Scriptures althrouch. And quhair Iohn Knox ſpeakis in general of meat, our contention was for bread and wine, quhilk I inferred ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarlie of the text. And deſires him to giue me
<pb facs="tcp:174733:32"/>
ane reſſon ſchortlie, grounded vpon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, quhairfore the phraſe alledged be me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the meat ſal not include bread and wine aſweil as his phraſe concerning the bread, be his opinion, without expres Scripture ſall include all kinde of vther meatis.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>I purge me firſt, that I neither burden my Lorde, with informalitie, neither yet, that his lordſhip, trauelleth by naturall reaſon onelie, to perſuade to man. But becauſe the whole ſtate of the cauſe (as I vnderſtand) ſtandeth in this, whether that Abraham and his ſouldiors broght back againe, ſuperfluitie of bread &amp; wine or not, I haue deſired the ſame to be prouen by the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed worde. The phraſe is not mine onely, but I did aggre with my Lorde,<note place="margin">Let all men iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dge if this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be not fuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient.</note> bringing in the ſame firſt. And now why I think that Abraham, and his, broght no ſuperfluitie of bread and wine back againe? the reaſon is, becauſe the text do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth plainlie affirme, that victualles, beſydes the other ſubſtance, wes caried away by the enimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. But that any victualles, beſydes the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce were broght back againe, there is no ſpecifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Becauſe I perceaue Iohn Knox, dois not meit the heid of my partickle quhair I do mark the conferrence, betuix the phraſes of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alledged be vs baith: quhairin (efter my iudgement) conſiſtes the marckis point of the purpoſe, I will trauell na further thairin, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174733:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that I haue ground of ye Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture abundantlie. And ſwa I wil go to ane v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heid, to aſſure the reader that Melchiſedec brocht not furth bread &amp; wine, to refreſch Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham and his company, I wil ground me proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon the text, and on this maner. The text ſayis, Protulit or proferens, quhilk is in the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar nomber as, ane, perſon bringand furth bread and wine, quhairfore neceſſarlie it concludes he brocht not furth bread and wine to refreſch ane multitude, as Abraham and his company was, quhllk was not poſſible to ane perſon to do: but onelie to mak Sacrifice conforme to my begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>What I haue anſwered, the beneuolent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhall after iudge, to the preſent coniecture of my Lorde, I anſwer that if Melchiſedec allone without al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany had broght onely furth ſo mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che bread &amp; wine, as he wes able goodly to carie, yet ſhal it not be neceſſarlie concluded that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he broght it not forth to gratifie Abraham, for an ſmall portion may oftentymes be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to many, but my Lorde appeareth to ſhoote at that ground, whiche I haue not laid for my principal. And therefore albeit his lordſhip ſhuld win it, yet my formar ſtrength were litle demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed (in my iudgement) for onles his lordſhip, be able to proue by the ꝑtaine wordes of the text that the bread and wine wer broght forth to be offered vnto God, my principall ground doeth alwayes abyde. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phraſe of the Scripture,
<pb facs="tcp:174733:33"/>
and als the ordinarie manere of ſpeaking, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth often tymes attribute to the principall man, that which at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, or wil is done, by his ſeruandes or ſubiectes, whereof I offer my ſelf, to ſhaw in Scriptures, mo teſtimonies then one, with tyme. And yet this is not my chief ground, but this I ſpeak for explaning of the text.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Of the formar pertickle I mark twa heides in ſpeciall, quhilk dois not onely giue apperance for my pretence, bot plainlie dois conuict, as the godlie and ineffectionat reader may cleirly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue. The firſt heid is, quhair Iohn Knox dois allege that Melchiſedec brocht furth bread and wine,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what ſhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fts my lord ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght.</note> to refreſch Abraham and his werie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, quhilk plainly differis fra his ſpeaking preſent, ſay and that it was to gratifie Abraham and his company, quhairinto thair is ſic mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt diffirence as it giues plaine perſuaſion, his ground in this heid to be nochtis. Secondly, it is againſt the ordur of nature, to think that ony ane man (lat be ane King and ane Preiſt) ſould bring furth that might gratifie, lat be to refreſch ſic ane multitude as, thre hundreth and auch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene werie perſonis.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>What my Lordes iudgement doeth moue in the harts of the auditure, I remitt to there own iudgement, but I plainly affirme: that neither in my worde, nor in my dytment is, there any ſuch repugnance or diffirence, as iuſtlie may conuict
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:174733:33"/>
me to haue an euil ground. For in my formar ſayinges, my wordes were, that by probable coniecture, the bread &amp; wine were broght forth by Melchiſedec, to refreſh Abraham and his we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie company. I did not affirme,<note place="margin">Note</note> that he and his whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie were thereof wholylie refreſhed. And in my latter wordes, I ſay, that albeit there had bene no more bread and wine, then Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedec onely broght forth, yet doeth it not thereof neceſſarlie conclude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame were not broght forth, to gratifie Abraham. In which maner of ſpeach, this terme gratifie, doeth nether repung, nor yet differ, from the terme refreſh, otherwiſe, commonlie doeth in maner of ſpeach Benus and Species, that is to ſay, the more generall, and the inferior. For in ſofar as Abraham and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany were refreſhed by the bread &amp; wine (were it neuer ſo litle) in ſofar doeth he bring it forth, to gratifie him. Proteſting plainly, that vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linglie I am compelled thus to anſwer.</p>
                           <p>And thus endeth the ſecond dayes trauell, all whole ſpent to anſwer my Lordes ſhifting.</p>
                           <p>Whereto he wes moued, becauſe he wes not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to proue that Melchiſedec offered bread and wine vnto God, as willinglie ones he tooke to proue.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>As dois Iohn Knox, ſa do I with all my hart, remit me to the iudgemente of the auditor, in this heid: and will not report the heides, of his formar pertickle for auoiding of prolixtnes.</p>
                           <p>But now will I conclude with ane argument.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <stage>
                           <pb facs="tcp:174733:34"/>And thus beginnes M. Quintyne the thrid day, hauing this argument written in paper which he cauſed to be red.</stage>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Quhatſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>euer opinion is conceaued of the Scip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of almichtie God, hauand na expres teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie nor apperance of the ſame, is alluterlie to be refuſed (as ſayis Iohn Knox him ſelf). Bot ſwa it is, that Iohn Knox a win opinion, conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aued or contracted of the Scripture, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the bringing forth of bread and wine, by Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedec, to refreſche or gratifie Abraham and his werie company, is not expreſly contened in the Scripture, nor hes na apperance of the ſamin: therefore it followis weill, that it is alluterlie be his awin iudgement to be refuſed.</p>
                           <p>Moued on godlie zeill (honorable auditor) that in this dangerous tyme, the treuth ſould cum to tryall, in ſic maner, as the conſcience of ſic, as ar perturbed (ſafar as lies in oure ſober poſſibilitie) ſould be eſtableſed, and at quietnes: we ſet furth certane artickles (as pleſed God to gif vs grace) vnto the quhilkis, Iohn Knox tuik on hand to mak impungnation: ſpecially to the artickle concerning the meſſe. Day houre &amp; place beand appointed and obſerued, I come to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my artickles, and in ſpeciall my artickle concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the meſſe.<note place="margin">Let the blindeſt amongs the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes iudge.</note> And according to the ſamin, tuik me properlie to my warrand, grounded vpone Goddes word: vnto the quhilk warrand, Iohn Knox, as ȝit hes maid na impungnation, bot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred me to ſuſtene and defend the name, the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the ceremonies, the opinion of men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:174733:34"/>
of the meſſe, and gif it wes ane Sacrifice Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatorie. I beand willed, that we ſchortlie ſould go to the ground, and effect, and ſubſtance of the purpoſe quhairfore we come, I ſtude be my artickle and warrand, as they ar written: not refuſand to defend, the heides aboue reheirſed, as tyme and place ſould ſerue. And notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that I was ſufficientlie grounded vpon Gods worde, quhilk I tuik to be my warrand,<note place="margin">Note that my Lorde confeſſes that he wes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſewer &amp; that he hes hurt his own cauſe.</note> and tuik lykewiſe vpon me, farr aboue my ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, the place and perſonage of ane defender: nottheles throuch occaſion that ſerued (as work will beir witnes) I was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to tak vpon me the perſonage of ane perſewer, farre by my appetit, ȝea, and the weill of my cauſe: and als by the opinion of all ſic as wald the weill of the ſamin, moued on godlie zeill (as God be iudge) that the trueth ſould cum to a tryal,<note place="margin">Sed ſero ſapiunt Poriges.</note> to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of God, and ſatiſfaction of the honorable auditor, I beand cled with the perſonage of ane impungnar, expres contrar to my mynd, for ſic cauſes as ar abone reheirſed, I maid impu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, not be manlie imaginationis, bot be the manifeſt worde of God. And that thre maner of wayes,<note place="margin">Let your freinds yet iudge</note> firſt to tak away Iohn Knox conceaued opinion, that Melchiſedec brocht furth bread &amp; wine, to refreſche or gratifie Abraham and his werie company, I called to remembrance, how that the ſpulȝeis of nyne Kingis, and of certain citeis to, was recouered be Abraham, quhairthr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouch, he and his company, was ſufficientlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſched, and had yneuch to be refreſched on, ſwa
<pb facs="tcp:174733:35"/>
that they miſtered not to be refreſhed with breid and wine of Melchiſedec. Secondlie quhair Io. Knox maid queſtion, that they had not bread &amp; wine. I returned againe to the text, to werifie the ſamin. Quhilk ſayes, and all thingis, perte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand vnto meat. Inferrand that in this phraſe, was contened bread and wine, conforme to the phraſe of the Scripture, quhair mention is maid onelie of bread, contenand all thingis neceſſar for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis ſuſtentacion, he find and this not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſatiſfaction. Ȝit ȝeid I not to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nis imagi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation, bot to the plaine text, and grounded me vpon the wordes of the text ſayand. Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedec brocht furth bread and wine. Inferrand, in that it was ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the thrid perſon ſingular,<note place="margin">How ſhal that be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</note> it was againſt the ordoure of nature, to think that ane ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſould bring furth (eſpecially he that was ane King and ane preiſt) to tak that paines to bring furth bread and wine, that micht grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie (lat be to refreſch) thre hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth and auchtene men. Seand that inuinſible perſuations, proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie gathered vpon the text,<note place="margin">But did nor does not ſo appeir to others.</note> could na wiſe bring Iohn Knox, to confeſſe that thing quhilk appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto me conforme to the Scriptures of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>michtie God, and all gude reſſon he ſould haue confeſſed. Then concluded I with the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Nor yet will do to hurt a iuſt cauſe</note> as I did begin, as my concluſion wil beir witnes, that he wald haue iuſtified his opinion conceiued of the Scripture, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>form to his awin ſayingis, be the expres word of God. And of my liberalitie wil grant him ȝit, gif he hes any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of apperance of the ſamin, notwithſtanding he ſaid to me, he wald not gif me ane hair of his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:174733:35"/>
heid, gif I ſould ſtand thir ſeuen ȝeires.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Proteſting firſt, that I may anſwer, in writ, vnto the formar argument (becauſe as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it wes before conceiued in writ) I enter in ſhortlie vnto the long diſcourſe, made by my Lorde: not willing to anſwer euerie part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but onely ſo muche, as may appear to infirme the iuſt cauſe. And firſt, where that my Lorde affirmeth, that I haue made no impungnation vnto his lordſhips artickle concerning the maſſe, I am content, that not onelie this honorable au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, but alſo the whole earth be iudge, in that point. For I haue plainly denied,<note place="margin">Note,</note> that ether the maſſe, hath approbation of the plaine worde of God, ether in name, action, opinion (to witt written of the maſſe, taucht of the maſſe, and in the conſcience of men, conceiued of the maſſe) &amp; finally that the actor therof, for his vſurped power, hath no greater aſſurance of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Which whole heades being denyed to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted, at the preſent, againſt my Lordrs artickle and ground, I did thus reaſon: that his lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip wes not able to proue that Chriſt Ieſus, in his latter Supper did offer his bodie and blood vnto God his Father, vnder the formes of bread and wine. His lordeſhip taking for his proue, the alledged Sacrifice of Melchiſedec in bread and wine, offered vnto God. I did lykewiſe deny, that Melchiſedec did at that tyme (to wit in the preſence of Abraham) offer ether bread or wine vnto God, which hath bene theſe two dayes by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt
<pb facs="tcp:174733:36"/>
in controuerſie betuix his lordeſhip and me. I haue alwayes denied, that the holy Spirit, in any notable or euident place of Scripture do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth affirme ſuche an ſacrifice to haue bene made by Melchiſedec vnto God: &amp; whil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I did hear no place of Scripture adduced, for the approbati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on thereof, my Lorde demandand of me, what then I thoght wes done with the bread &amp; wine, I anſwered, that albeit, I wes not bound to giue my iudgement, becauſe that he wes bound to proue his affirmatiue (as yet I ſay he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d) and thereof I wilbe content,<note place="margin">Conſid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what iudges I admit</note> that his lordſhipes moſte fauorable freindes, of beſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, yea, euen if his Lordeſhip pleaſe, the Lordes of the Seſſion, be iudges in that point. I anſwered, I ſay, that be coniecture, the bread and wine were broght furth by Melchiſedec, to refreſhe Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, and his werie company. Vpon which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, his lordſhip (how iuſtlie let all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge) did cleith him ſelf againe,<note place="margin">Contrar the obiec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made of impoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſibilitie &amp; that it was aga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedec al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uld bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g forth bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ad. &amp;c.</note> without my procure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the perſonage of ane impungnar.</p>
                           <p>And did adduce ſuche thinges, as beſt pleaſed his lordſhip, whereto I did anſwer, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole conference will report, and as I ſuppoſe, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlie to euerie thing obiected, except that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my Lord did not touche the expoſition al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgede by me, vpon the wordes, Melchiſedec allone did bring forth bread and wine (as my Lorde alledgeth) I differed to bring in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Scriptures, to proue that it is an thing in Scripture verrie commone, that the thing, that is done at the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand of any notable
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:174733:36"/>
perſone, is attributed vnto him ſelf, althogh it be done, be ſeruandes or ſubiectes at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, which I do now ſhortlie. It is ſaid in Scripture, that Noie did all that God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him: and plaine it is, that God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded him to make the Arck,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.7.</note> which wes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> building the full ſpace of a hundreth yeares. God further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to furniſh the Arck with all kynde of victualles, which the text affirmeth, that he did. Now if we ſhal conclude, that Noie allone cutted euerie tree, Noie allone did hew euerie tree, and ſo forth: it appeareth to me that we ſhal conclude a great abſurditie. The ſame is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Dauid, of whome mention is made, that he being Prophet and King,<note place="margin">2 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>
                              </note> deuided to the whole people, yea, vnto the whole multitude of Iſrael, yea, bothe to men and women, an portion of bread, an portion of fleſh, and an portion of wine.</p>
                           <p>If we ſhall think, that Dauid did this with his own hand, we ſhall conclude in my appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> formar abſurditie. The ſame is manifeſt by many other phraſes, yea, and by our daylie maner of ſpeaking. And therefore yet as of before. I think my Lordes expoſition coact, in that he will admit none to haue broght forth the bread and wine, but Melchiſedec allone. But howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be, it moueth me nothing, for vnto ſuche tyme, as that my Lorde, in plaine wordes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by the holy Goſte, proue that Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedec, did offer vnto God bread and wine: he hath prouen nothing of that, which he took on hand to proue. And therefore I greatlie feare,
<pb facs="tcp:174733:37"/>
that whill that,<note place="margin">The beſt ground, culd find no grou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the word of God.</note> which his lordeſhip calleth the beſt, is ſo long in finding an ſure ground within the Scripture, that the reſt in the end, be found altogether groundles, at the leaſt within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke of God. And therefore I deſyre, as of before, to hear his lordſhipes probation of the principal.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>I am ſorie that we ar contrined on this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to driue tyme, ather parteis in iuſtification of his a win cauſe: bot wiſſes quicklie to go to the markis point, as I haue euer done, conforme to my artickle and to my warrand: and makis the haile warld to iudge, quhither it is my deutie, efter formall reſſoning, to defend the ſaides ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickles, or to proue, or to impung. Quhair Iohn Knox makis ane meine, that I haue brocht my argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or purpoſes in writ: quhat I haue in worde or writ, or vtherwayes, I praiſe God.</p>
                           <p>Bot the trueth is, according to my cuſtome, I maid memorie, efter my repoſe, of ſic heides, as I thocht, I was able to haue buſines ado with all. And that I did be the grace of God onely, not that I am eſchamed to be learned with ony man that wil teach me. And as to the concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his partickle, quhair he dois mak meine, yat I haue na grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the Scripture for the meſſe (as he beleuis) will God ſall fruſtrat his expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in that,<note place="margin">When ye perform promes let men beleue you.</note> and all vthers. And aſſures him will God ſall iuſtifie the meſſe als ſufficientlie, conforme to my artickle, as he and all the reſt of his opinion in chriſtendome, ſalbe able to iuſtifie be expres Scripture, or ony vther meine, that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:174733:37"/>
Ieſus Chriſte is ane ſubſtance with the Father.<note place="margin">Homonſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſiue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lis</note> And that it be not thocht that thir ar wantone wordes, like as the mater ſould not cum to pas, bot that I wald trifle the mater: I will deſyre Iohn Knox maiſt humblie &amp; hartlie, for Chriſtes ſaike, lat vs go ſchortlie without trifling to the purpoſe, and lat wark beir witnes. And ſwa re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, to reſume my argument, and ſay thereto formalie as effeires.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Becauſe that euerie man muſte giue accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes before God, not onely of his workes, but alſo of his wordes and thoghts. I will make no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proteſtation, whether that I haue defended hitherto my own opinion, or a manifeſt treuth, or whether that I haue impungned any treuth of God, or a manifeſt lie (let this be ſaid with reuerence of all perſones, for the iuſtnes of the cauſe) leauing, I ſay, the iudgement to God: I ſay that I haue in plaine termes iuſtlie oppung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned bothe the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, broght forth by my Lord, for defence of his artickle. For in plaine wordes, I haue denied, that Ieſus Chriſte, into his lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Supper, did make any Sacrifice of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and blood, vnder the formes of bread and wine, vnto God his Father. And lykewiſe I haue denyed, that Melchiſedec did offer vnto God, bread and wine as of before. which grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, becauſe my Lorde hath not hitherto ꝓuen, I muſt hold them as impunged and oppu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gned: euer whill, I hear the ground of Melchiſedec, plainly prouen, by plaine Scripture (to wit)
<pb facs="tcp:174733:38"/>
that the plaine Scripture ſay, that Melchiſedec offered vnto God bread and wine:<note place="margin">Let my lord an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer when he pleaſes.</note> or that it be of any plaine and euident Scripture, plainlie conuicted, that ſo he did. His lordſhip, oght not to think it ſtrange, althogh I require to anſwer in writ, to that argument, which his Lordeſhip hath ꝓponded, conceaued before, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in writ, for ſuch I take to be, the libertie of all fre diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>putations. Whoſe lauboure it wes, or is, I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing regard. For ſo long as God doeth miniſter vnto me, ſpirit &amp; life, with iudgement and habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I intend (by his grace) til oppu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, that which in my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience I hold to be damnable idolatrie. And where his lordſhip ſayeth, that he is als a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to affirme the maſſe (which I impung) to be the ordinance of God, as that I or any of my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, is able to proue Ieſus Chriſte to be one ſubſtance with the Father:<note place="margin">Let the godlie iudge if the maſſe &amp; Chriſt Ieſus &amp; his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie oght to hing in one bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance.</note> with reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his lordſhipes perſonage blood, and honor, and with the reuerence &amp; pacience, of the whole auditor, I ſay, that the aſſercion is not onelie raſhe, but alſo moſte dangerous, yea, and in a part blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous. For, for to compare the greateſt myſterie, yea, the whole aſſurance of our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with that, which as it hath bene vſed, hath no appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of Gods worde (for that I haue impu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and intendes to impung) can not lack ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, of a lightlie eſteaming of our redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And to cut the matter ſhort, the formar queſtion being decided (to wit whither that Melchiſedec, did offer vnto God bread and wine) I offer my ſelf, without further delay, to proue, that Ieſus
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:174733:38"/>
Chriſte, is of one ſubſtance with the Father: and that by the euident teſtimonies of Gods Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And therefore yet as of before, I humbly require his lordeſhip, to prepare him for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the formar, to witt, of the oblation of Melchiſedec.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>Quhair Iohn Knox dois affirme, that in plaine termis, he hes iuſtlie impunged, baith ye grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, brocht furth be me, for defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of my artickles. I anſwer, I deny that he hes maid ony impu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. And quhair he ſayes, that in plaine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, he hes denied, that Ieſus Chriſte, into his latter Supper, did make ony Sacrifice of his bodie and blude, vnder the formes of bread and wine, vnto God his Father: or that Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec did offer vnto God bread and wine,<note place="margin">Your warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is ſo weak that it neides no other impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſay it is not</note> as of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. I anſwer, that it is his deutie to mak im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnation, to my aſſercion, conform to my war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand, for denying, is na proper nor ſufficient im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnation. And quhair he ſayes, that becauſe I haue not hidderto prouen the ſaides grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis. &amp;c. I anſwer, that it is my deutie to defend and not to preif, conform to my artickle, &amp; my war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand. And quhair he deſyres tyme to anſwer to my argument, ꝓponed this day in writ, I frely grant it vnto him. And quhair Iohn Knox ſayes,<note place="margin">Then ye ouerſaw yourſelf.</note> yat my aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not onely raſhe, bot alſo maiſt dangerous, ȝea, and in ane pairt, blaſphemous. I anſwer, that quhair he ſayes, I am to raſhe: I wis his modeſtnes in this ſamin, ſic as becu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ane ſinceir chriſtiane, like as he is reckned to
<pb facs="tcp:174733:39"/>
be.<note place="margin">Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mie is blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it.</note> And quhair he callis my aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ane pairt blaſphemous: than had bene tyme to haue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it blaſphemie, quhen he had prouen it in deid ſufficientlie. And quhair he ſayes, it is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, thair is na danger, it be and vnderſtand, as I ſay, and treulie meines. For I am mair nor aſſured, that Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, is ane ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with the Father,<note place="margin">Not as papiſtes haue v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it.</note> &amp; als that Ieſus Chriſt is the author and inſtitutor of the meſſe. And ſwa dois not ane veritie, mak impugnation to ane vther. Bot in this maner of ſpeaking, I wil plaine my induſtrie, giuen vnto me be the grace of God,<note place="margin">Aduerr what ye ſpeak.</note> willing to contrafit the wiſdome and prudence, of the wiſe and prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t medicinar (for we are, and ſould be of reſſon, medicinars to the ſaule) for lyke as the prudent medicinar, dois expell ane vennome or poyſome, be contrapoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone. Swa wald I expel the damnable heriſies, of the Caluiniſtes,<note place="margin">My lord wolde haue bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen if this byle had not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> Lutherians, and Accolam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padians, againſt ye bliſſed Sacrifice of ye meſſe, be conference with the damnable heriſies of the Arrians, quha did alledge ten teſtimonies of Scripture for ane, geuand mair appearance, to preif that Chriſt was not ane ſubſtance with the Father: nor dois the Caluiniſtes, Lutherians, and Aecolampadians, to preif that the meſſe, is idolatrie: as I fall ſufficientlie iuſtifie, as may ſtand to the glorie of God, and weil of my cauſe. To the latter pairt, quhair he ſayes, to cut the mater ſchort, the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>nar queſtion be and decided (to wit quhither that Melchiſedec did offer breid and wine vnto God or not) he offeris him ſelfe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174733:39"/>
without farther delay, to proue yat Ieſus Chriſt is ane ſubſtance with the Father. &amp;c. I anſwer to the hinder pairt of this partickle. I wis of God, he and all vthers of his opinion miſtered als lytle probation or perſuaſion, to the ane, as I do to the vther, as I wald ſay, to beleue the meſſe, to be the inſtitution of Chriſt Ieſus, as I do mair nor aſſuredlie beleue, Chriſte to be ane ſubſtance with the Father,<note place="margin">That ar you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer able to do.</note> and deſyres na pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation thereof: bot ſall God will and preif ye ane be the Scripture als expres, as he ſall preif ye vther. And quhair he humblie deſyres me, to prepair me for the probatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the formar (to wit of the oblation of Melchiſedec) I humblie and hartlie deſyre Iohn Knox, as he will teſtifie his feruor, that the treuth cum to ane tryall, and as he will ſatiſfie the expectation of the noble audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, that he will mak impugnation formallie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deutie, to my laſt argument and concluſion.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Where my Lord to vnburden him ſelf of that, which by all reaſon, he oght to ſuſteane, to wit, to proue his affirmatiue, by him ſelf proponed,<note place="margin">Your lordſhip took to proue your gr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ound by the text, and that you haue not don.</note> ſayeth, that to deny, is not properlie to impung. I anſwer, that in that cace, it is moſte proper. For he that ꝓponeth for him ſelf an affirmatiue, and his aduerſar denying the ſame, is euer ſtill bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the probation thereof, and the aduerſar hath euer ſtill impungned it, vnto he proue it, and thereupon I deſire iudgement. To the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, I ſtil affirme that it is his lordſhips deutie,
<pb facs="tcp:174733:40"/>
to proue his affirmatiue, whereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtandeth the victorie of his whole cauſe: w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is be me in plaine wordes denyed. To the thrid, I thank his lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hartlie,<note place="margin">And that he hes receaued</note> and promiſes vnto him an anſwer, againe in writ, this preſent conference being put to an ſufficient end. To the fourt. As my prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation will witnes, I ſpeak againſt the aſſercio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onelie and not againſt the perſone: whiche yet (in my iudgement) lacketh not ſuſpicion of the formar crimes. For howſoeuer my Lord be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded of the ground and aſſurance of the meſſe (the aſſurance whereof I haue not yet hard) I my ſelf am fully aſſured, that there be mo then ten thouſand, which euidentlie do knowe, the vanitie and impietie of that maſſe, which I haue impungned: who nottheles, moſte conſtantlie beleue Ieſus Chriſte, to be of one ſubſtance with the Father: yea, that do beleue, whatſoeuer by the Scriptures of God, can be prouen neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaluation of man. Therefore yet againe, I ſay, that to lay in any maner of equalitie, that which is moſte ſure, and that which was neuer yet plainlie prouen by the Scriptures of God, to be the inſtitution of Ieſus Chriſt: is more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the crymes foreſaid, then that I can be ſubiect to any ſuſpicion of immodeſtie for my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar wordes. To the blaſphemie, I anſwer, as before. Immediatlie to the ſext. How that euer my Lord vnderſtandeth and meaneth, that his lordſhip is als able, to proue the maſſe to be the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus Chriſt, as I am able to proue Chriſt, to be one ſubſtance with the Father: I
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:174733:40"/>
think that an great nomber will think my lords affirmation, verrie hard to be prouen. And I my ſelf will ſtill continually dout, vnto the tyme, I hear the probation led. To the ſeuent, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Lordes compariſon of the mediciner, and of his lordſhips induſtrie. What the paſtors of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church oght to be, the Scriptures plainly do teach vs: but what vniuerſallie they haue bene theſe nyne hundreth yeares bypaſt, hiſtories, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and recent memorie, hath taught vs, yea, and preſentlie do teach vs: to the great greif of all Chriſtianitie. Where that his lordſhip do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in plaine termes, condempn the Caluiniſtes, Lutherians and Aecolampadians, of heriſie: I wold haue required of his lordſhip delay of time, according to his deſyre of me, vnto the tyme, that there cauſe had bene ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlie tried, in an lawfull, vniuerſal counſell, deulie indicted, and conuened. But where that he compareth, the doctrine of the forenamed, with the damnable hereſie, of Arrius: I wold lykewiſe haue wiſhed vnto his lordſhip greater foreſight, in ſo graue a mater. For howſoeuer the Arrians appeared to abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in teſtimonies of Scriptures, without all ground, indiſtinctlie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſted (and that becauſe they made no diffreence betuix the two natures in Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">Let my lorde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>.</note> but did fooliſhlie appropriat to the Godhead, that, which did onelie aperteane to the manlie nature) yet think I, that my lord ſhall neuer be able, by plaine Scripture, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pung any chief head, ether affirmed, or denyed, in doctrine of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the foreſaides perſons:
<pb facs="tcp:174733:41"/>
lyke as did the godly and learned in there ages, the foreſaid damnable heriſie. To the laſt, I haue alreadie promiſed to anſwer, to my Lordes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in writ: and therefore oght not to be bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened with it now, eſpeciallie becauſe it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our formar ground, and doeth not properlie aperteane to the cauſe. And yet therefore now laſt for concluſion, that we ſhal not be compelled continually to repeat on thing, I deſyre my lord according to his deutie, and reaſon of diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Heir my lord ſtay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed &amp; for anſwer offerred to me a book.</note> to bring forth his probation of his two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar groundes, be me plainly denyed.</p>
                           <p>This conference being ended, for this tyme, my Lorde preſentlie did riſe, for trouble of body, and then Iohn Knox, did ſhortlie reſume, the principall groundes. And becauſe the noblemen heir aſſembled, were altogether deſtitute of all ꝓuiſion, bothe for hors and man, the ſaid Iohn, humblie required the foreſaid Lord, that it wold pleaſe him to go to Air, where that better eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment migh be had for all eſtates. Which becauſe my Lord vtterlie refuſed, the ſaid Iohn deſired when that the ſaid conference ſhould be ended. My Lorde did promes, that vpon licence pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed,<note place="margin">Whither I haue ſo done or nor mo then them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues can witnes.</note> of the Quenes maieſtie, and her honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble counſell, that he wold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peir in Edinburgh, and there, in there preſence, finiſh the ſaid confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. The ſaid Iohn did promes, to trauel with the ſecret counſel, that the ſaid licence might be obteined. And deſired the foreſaid Lorde, to do the lyke with the Quenes maieſtie, whereupon the ſaid Iohn Knox, took inſtruments and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuments.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <pb n="29" facs="tcp:174733:41"/>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>At the concluſion of our reſſoning,<note place="margin">The anſwer wes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo that it apperte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aned not to me to proue my inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertened to my lord to proue that mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec offerred &amp;c. But that can not my lord vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand</note> I gaif Iohn Knox ane argument in writ, deſiring him that he wald iuſtifie his opinion be expres teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Scripture, or ony apperance thereof. Quhairto the ſaid Iohn required tyme to gif anſwer, and the tyme, micht nawiſe ſerue, of farder reſſoning, for ſic cauſes, as ar compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in the ſaid Iohn Knox writing. And as toward his deſyre of me to Air, treulie it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing that I micht not preſentlie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modiouſly do. Bot alwayes, I will copeir before ye Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes grace, and ſic as hit grace, pleſis to take to be auditors, to defend the ſaides artickles, and in ſpecial the artickle concerning the meſſe, as thay ar written, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>en and quhair it be hir grace pleſure, ſwa that the habilitie of my bodie will ſerue ony wiſe as I hope to God it ſall, to quhom be praiſe glorie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor for euer.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Croſraguell</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                     <div type="dialogue">
                        <pb facs="tcp:174733:42"/>
                        <head>The anſwer to my Lordes laſt argument, proponed by him in writ, the laſt day of diſputation. The argument is this.</head>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>M. Quintyne.</speaker>
                           <p>
                              <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatſumeuer opinion, is conceaued of the Scriptures of almichty God, hauand na expres teſtimonie nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance of the ſamin: is vtterlie to be refuſed, as ſayes Iohn Knox him ſelf. Bot ſwa it is, that Iohn Knox a win opinion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued or contracted of the Scripture, concerning the bringing furth of bread and wine, be Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec, to refreſh or gratifie, Abraham and his werie company, is not expreſly conteined in the Scripture, nor hes na apperance of the ſamin, thairfore it fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> wis wei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, that it is all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>terlie be his awin iudgement to be refuſed.</p>
                        </sp>
                        <sp>
                           <speaker>Iohn Knox.</speaker>
                           <p>Yf I ſhould grant vnto you, my Lorde your whole argument, I ſhould but declare my ſelf ignorant of the art, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>lyndful of my owne affirmation: but yet had ye prouen nothing of your intent. The chief queſtion, and controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie betuix you and me, is not whether that my interpretation of that place which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                                 <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                              </gap> your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                                 <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                              </gap> not: but whether that Melchiſedec the figure of Chriſte, did offer vnto God bread &amp; wine, whiche ye haue affirmed, and haue laid it to be the ground and cauſe, why it behoued Chriſte Ieſus, to haue made
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:174733:42"/>
oblation of his bodie and blood, vnder the form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of bread and wine, in his latter Supper. Which bothe I denyed. So that it reſts to you to proue, that Melchiſedec the figure of Chriſt, did offer vnto God bread and wine. &amp;c. And ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteines not vnto me, to proue my opinion, nor interpretation. For ſuppoſing that my opinion, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued of that place were to be reiected (as ye are neuer able to proue it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>e) yet is your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue, neuer the better prouen, for if ye will conclude: it wes not broght forth to refreſh A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham (which yet is not prouen) ergo it wes broght forth to be offered vnto God: babes will mock you, and ſend you againe to your logick. But yet my Lord with your leaue I muſt come nerar you, and ſay, that the maior or firſt part of your argument is fals and that ye falſly alledge vpon me, that which I neuer ſpak nor ment.</p>
                           <p>Read the whole conference betuix you and me, and ye ſhall not find that I haue ſimple affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that all opinion of man, conceaued of the Scriptures, is vtterlie to be reiected: onles the ſame be prouen by the manifeſt worde of God. For I am not ignorant that ſome interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ar tollerable, yea, and may be to the edification of the Church, althogh they do not fully expres, the minde of the holie Goſte, in that place. But I haue affirmed, and yet affirmes, that nether the authoritie of the Church, the determination of the counſell, nor the opinion of the doctor, is to be receaued in matters of faith, &amp; in the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine concerning our ſaluation: onles the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:174733:43"/>
be prouen by the expres word of God. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Lord, with your leaue, I muſt ſay, that ether wilfully or els by ſome ouerſight, ye haue omitted bothe in the maior &amp; in the minor of your argument, that which ſhould haue bene, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe and aſſurance of your concluſion. For thus ye oght to haue reaſoned. Whatſoeuer opinion is conceaued of the Scripture of almightie God, concerning faith and the doctrine of Saluation, hauing no expres teſtimonie of the ſame, is to be reiected. But ſo it is, that Iohn Knox owne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, concerning the bringing forth of bread and wine by Melchiſedec, is a matter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faith, and the doctrine of our Saluation, and yet hath no teſtimonie of Gods expreſſed worde: therefore it is to be reiected. Yf on this maner ye had reaſoned, my Lord, (as of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ye muſt do, if ye conclude any thing againſt me) I wold haue immediatlie denied the ſecond part of your argument, and haue ſaid: that to know or define, what wes done with the bread and wine, broght out by Melchiſedec, is no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickle of our beleue, nether yet is it a doctrine, neceſſarie to the Saluation of man. For nether did Adam, Abel, Seth, Enos, Henoch, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſalem, nor Noie, beleue any ſuche thing, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet is there ſince the dayes of Abraham, any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement giuen by God, to beleue ſuche an artickle, yea, further in the whole Scriptures, there is no mention made what wes done with that bread and wine, and therefore it can be no artickle of our beleue, nor yet no doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:174733:43"/>
our Saluation, and ſo hath your argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment broken the owne neck. Yf I liſt, my Lord to ſport a lytill with you, I might find ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion in the ſecond part of your argument. For where ye affirme that my opinion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the bringing forth of the bread and wine, by Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedec, to refreſh Abraham and his companie, is nether expreſly conteined in the word of God, nether yet hath appearance of the ſame: and therefore vtterlie it is to be reiected. Now my Lorde giue me leaue, to turne this part of your argument in your owne boſome, if I can, and that ſo I may do, thus I reaſon.</p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>The opinion</hi> conceaued by my Lorde Abbote, concerning bread and wine, broght forth by Melchiſedec to be offered vnto God, is not expreſly conteined in Gods Scriptures, therefore it is vtterlie to be reiected. Bewarre my Lorde, that ye be not beaten with your own batton:<note place="margin">Let my lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt this</note> for then muſt the maſſe, yea, the beſt part of the ſame, ſtand vpon an vnſure ground, that is to ſay, vpon the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of man, and hauing no aſſurance of Gods expreſſed worde. But now my Lorde, meryues ſet aſyde, I humblie require you, by my pen, as I did by mouth, that depelie ye conſider, with what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience before God, ye da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> affirme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine to be holſome, yea, &amp; neceſſary to be beleued,
<pb facs="tcp:174733:44"/>
ye are able to bring no prufe out of the manifeſt word of God. The ſecond day of our conference and diſputation, when I wes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, your treuole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iectures and vanities: your bragges and boſte, ofter blowen out then ones, were, that your probation ſhould be ſo euident, that the ſtones ſhould heare your probation, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead walles ſhould ſe the iuſtnes of your cauſe. I paciently did abyde (althogh perchance with the greif of ſome brethren) theſe your wantone wordes, and thoght with my ſelf Parturiunt mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. &amp;c. But what is now produced and broght forth; the world may ſe. It may appeare that ye were hard beſet, when for to auoide the prufe of your owne affirmatiue, ye fled to impugne, that which apperteaneth nothing to the purpoſe. For as I wes not bound to haue ſhewen vnto you what I thoght wes done with the bread and wine, broght forth by Melchiſedec, ſo wes I not bound to haue defended, my interpretation and iudgement of that place: but vnto you it alway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es aperteineth (and if euer we meit againe vpon that head, it wilbe yet iudged to aperteine to you) to proue that Melchiſedec, did at that time offer bread and wine vnto God, which I am well aſſured, that ye are neuer able to do, by any teſtimonie of Gods worde.<note place="margin">Note.</note> And therefore muſt I ſay, the maſſe ſtandeth groundles. And the greateſt pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap> thereof, for all his ſicker riding hath ones loſte his ſtirropes, yea, is altogether ſet beſydes his ſadil. And yet the common brute goeth, that ye my Lorde, your flatterers, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:174733:44"/>
collateralles brag greatlie of your victorie, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined in diſputation againſt Iohn Knox, but I will not beleue you to be ſo vaine onles I ſhall knowe the certantie by your owen hand writ.</p>
                           <p>Let all men now iudge vpon what ground the Sacrifice of the maſſe ſtandeth. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father hath not planted within his Scriptures ſuche a doctrine. It followeth therefore that it oght to be rooted out of all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes hartes.</p>
                        </sp>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <trailer>the end</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at Edinburgh by Robert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ekpreuk. Cum priuilegio. 1563.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
